<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The happy union of England and Holland, or, The advantageous consequences of the alliance of the Crown of Great Britain with the States General of the United Provinces</title>
            <author>R. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W94</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08251248</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08251248</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1243:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The happy union of England and Holland, or, The advantageous consequences of the alliance of the Crown of Great Britain with the States General of the United Provinces</title>
                  <author>R. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedicatory epistle signed: R.W.</note>
                  <note>Translated from the Dutch?</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41191:1"/>
            <p>THE Happy Union OF ENGLAND AND HOLLAND: OR, THE Advantagious CONSEQUENCES OF THE ALLIANCE OF THE <hi>CROWN</hi> of GREAT BRITAIN WITH THE <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Licenſed,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>May the <hi>20th.</hi> 1689.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41191:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41191:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend <hi>Father</hi> in <hi>God Gilbert</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Happy Conſequences</hi> of a ſettl'd <hi>Alliance</hi> and <hi>Union</hi> between their <hi>Majeſties</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> are that which theſe few Sheets have undertak'n to make out; as being neceſſary for the ſafety and repoſe of both in particular, and of the <hi>Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in general. How zealouſly <hi>Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> has always Labour'd the Advancement of the Latter, and how Inſtrumental you have been to promote the Former, is not unknown to all the World. For this reaſon, the <hi>Author</hi> of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> really intended for the good of both Nations, is ſo Ambitious as he is, to appear in the <hi>Engliſh Dialect,</hi> under <hi>Your Lordſhip's</hi> Patronage and Protection from the Cenſures of thoſe, who make it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to diſturb the Public Tranquility both of
<pb facs="tcp:41191:3"/>
               <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> Not doubting through <hi>Your Lordſhips</hi> Favour of the ſame Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here, as the Original had in the place that gave it Birth; Yet humbly craving on the other ſide, <hi>Your Lordſhips</hi> Pardon, for the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this <hi>Addreſs;</hi> which ſpeaks, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the High Eſteem and Honour that all Men, who value the true Religion, the Laws and Liberties of their Country, have for <hi>Your Perſon;</hi> but more eſpecially of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, and Moſt Obedient Servant, R. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41191:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of a <hi>Union</hi> between the <hi>ENGLISH</hi> and <hi>HOLLANDERS.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>USually we judge, by the Event, of the Uprightneſs or Injuſtice of human Actions, and of the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or Indiſcretion of thoſe that Act. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers take upon them to make their Comments upon theſe inconſiderate Judgments, That vulgar Opinion car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it, That is to ſay, that they who proſper paſs for Wiſe, and many times for Vertuous Men; they who are unfortunate are lookt upon as imprudent; and ſometimes which is worſe, as wicked and impious. A Kingdom oppreſs'd with exactions becomes enrag'd againſt the Contrivers of their Miſery, and revolts againſt thoſe that Officiate in the Tyrannies of the Court. Therefore Forces are ſent to quell and diſſipate the mutinous Multitude, their Ringleaders are ſeiz'd, and put to Death by all the moſt infamous and cruel ways of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; nor do they grant any Act of Oblivion to the reſt, but by charging them with new Taxes and Impoſitions. And as a Conſummation of their Misfortunes, their Poſterity at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all their Miſeries to them, and Hiſtorians range them in the Number of Factious and Rebels, juſtly depriv'd of their Liberties and their Ancient Priviledges. For theſe thirty Years the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have labour'd to render themſelves Abſolute, they have gradually diſpoyl'd the Cities and Corporations of their Charters, and made it their buſineſs to introduce Popery into their three Kingdoms: well knowing that the Alteration of the Eſtabliſh'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion trailes after it the Change of the Government and the Laws; and no leſs aſſur'd, that of all the Chriſtian Sects, the <hi>Roman</hi> is that which beſt agrees with Arbitrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and is moſt proper to inſpire blind Obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41191:4"/>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> weary'd with their Sufferings, privately call in the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and that great <hi>Hero</hi> was receiv'd into the <hi>Iſland</hi> as their <hi>Tutelar-Angel,</hi> but with ſo much Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Unanimity, that the ſuddain Commotion was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken rather for a public Rejoycing then a Rebellious Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Some make haſt to meet him, others ſet up his Standard, while the King diſturb'd in Mind, perplex'd and aſtoniſh'd, withdraws without ſtriking a ſtroak, and puniſhes himſelf with a voluntary Exile, for having followed the Advice of his Evil Counſellors. All <hi>Europe</hi> admires ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain a Revolution. The Proteſtants lookt upon him as a Prodigy of Heaven, ſent for the relief of Truth oppreſs'd. The moderate <hi>Catholics</hi> acknowledge the Juſtice of the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Deſigns, applaud the mildneſs which he exerciſes toward their Brethren, and impute the unkindneſs which he has for their Religion, at this Conjucture, to the violent Counſels of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> The Politicians of both Parties look upon the Succeſs, as the Effect of a Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Genius, which Heaven has been pleas'd to Favour, whether to ſet Enſlav'd <hi>Europe</hi> at Liberty, or whether it were to ſhew that Prudence and Mildneſs are more aſſur'd and efficacious means to attain their Ends, then the Sanguinary Maxims of <hi>Matchiavel. Laſtly,</hi> Perſons of the cleareſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellects, and moſt perſpicacious inſight into Affairs, belive that nothing can be above the reach of that Prince who has ſhewn himſelf able to carry on for many Years a Deſign of ſo great Importance unknown to his Enemies, or any other, who had no occaſion to be intereſted therein. A Prince who has United ſeveral Soveraign Potentates againſt <hi>France;</hi> who has ſo well managed the Inclination and Humours of three Kingdoms, of ſeveral diſtant Plantations, and a Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Commonwealth, for a long time haraſs'd by various Factions, as to ſoder them into Unanimity. A Prince in a Word, who after he has taken time to reflect and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, puts his Reſolutions in Execution with a courage and ſwiftneſs beyond imagination.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41191:4"/>'Tis true, the Sloath, the lgnorance, and the Neceſſity which conſtrains ſome Men to ſubmit to a preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, and to ſide with the ſtrongeſt Party, are without queſtion the real ſources of thoſe applauſes, which are given to thoſe whom happy Succeſs has exalted above others. Add to this that how deſirous ſo ever Men may be to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate themſelves with ſuch Perſons, yet they are always willing to act conformably to their own Underſtandings. So that <hi>Self-Love,</hi> being willing to reconcile theſe two Paſſions, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwades us, that our Flatteries are juſt, and that the Grandees are beholding to their Merit for their advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Moreover it is moſt certain that theſe ſucceſsful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are many times highly worthy of Honour, and that Prudence and Indiſcretion are the moſt uſual cauſes of the good or bad Succeſs of Men; of which, they who only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the moſt known Circumſtances of the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>England,</hi> may convince themſelves with little trouble.</p>
               <p>But if Men are ſo quick in judging of things done, on the other ſide, they are ſo ſlow, to determin when they ought to Act, that their miſtiming Execution, or their Wavering and Heſitation becomes the diſappointment of the greateſt and moſt noble Deſigns. They whoſe Intereſt it is to oppoſe them fill their Minds with pannic Fears, or deſperate Miſtruſts and Jealouſies; and in regard that the number of Perſons timorous and jealous, are very numerous; and for that idle, and imaginary Fear works a more ſignal Effect upon ſuch, then a hope and aſſurance grounded upon Reaſon, therefore that a Man may act with Prudence upon ſuch occaſions, it behoves him to take a convenient time to examin the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Time, of Places and Perſons, and then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, and purſue his deſign by the ſhorteſt ways and means, provided they be honeſt and lawful.</p>
               <p>If a Man may be permitted to deliberate before he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages in an Enterprize, the ſame Liberty is not allowed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41191:5"/>
him, after once he has began the Execution of it; for that the Ignominy is no leſs, then the danger to abandon a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Undertaking. Every moment that a Man looſes in conſulting whether he ſhall go on or no, are as ſo many foot of ground which a Man ſurrenders to his Enemy, and as ſo many paces that he retreats from his Adverſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> have Contracted a moſt ſtrait Alliance one with another by Vertue of that Aid and Aſſiſtance with which the <hi>States General</hi> furniſh'd his Royal Highneſs <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> toward the Reſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Laws and Religion, under Oppreſſion and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany, in that Iſland. Now certain it is, that if theſe two Nations continue a good Correſpondence, they will be the Terror of their Enemies, the Sanctuary of their Neighbours, the ſupport of their Allies, and it may be the Reſtorers of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> to her Liberties. There is nothing appears capable in all probability to prevent the Effects of this Union, but the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Credit which ſome weak and inadvertent People may give to Spies, or other Perſons corrupted by the <hi>French,</hi> who labour to buz into their Ears imaginary future Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences and Diſturbances. But tho' there be very little likelihood that ſuch ill-diſpos'd People ſhould ever get the Upper-hand, or make any conſiderable Progreſs in their Deſigns; Nevertheleſ, whether it be out of my abundance of precaution, or that it is a pleaſing thing to let the World know that a Man has Reaſon of his ſide, I thought it my duty to oblige the public, by ſhewing how weak the Pretenſions of thoſe People are who argue againſt this Union and the real Intereſt of theſe two Nations to preſerve it invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable.</p>
               <p>All that their Enemies can invent of moſt plauſible to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate into the two Nations a Miſtruſt of the Prince, or a Jealouſie of one another, is to be reduc'd to theſe Six Heads. 1. That a King or Regent in <hi>England,</hi> being likewiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour or <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of the United Provinces is too pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41191:5"/>
2. That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> being both for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable by Sea, and gaining their Principal Riches by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Trade, can never flouriſh but by the ſubduing of the one to the other. 3. That the two Nations being thus Jealous of their mutual Proſperity, it will be eaſie for a Politic Prince to make uſe of the one to invade the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Priviledges of the other. 4. That the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> being a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> will favour the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and permit the Puritan Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> to keep their Station on purpoſe to weaken the Epiſcopal Party in <hi>England.</hi> 5. That this Prince has already given great Proofs of his Activity and Policy, by acquiring more Power in the United Provinces then any of his Predeceſſors, and by engaging the <hi>States General</hi> in the Expedition into <hi>England</hi> without any Engagement that could urge them to it. 6. That tho' the Prince himſelf were never ſo ſincere in his own intentions, as he cannot be in two places at one time, it will not be poſſible for him to ſatisfy two Nations always accuſtom'd to ſee their Prince at home among them, and to enjoy him intirely to themſelves; and that therefore let him divide his time after what manner ſoever he pleaſes, it will be a difficult Matter for him to pleaſe both the one and the other.</p>
               <p>1. I muſt acknowledge, in the firſt place, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants never yet had ſo potent a Prince, as the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is like at one time or other to be, if it pleaſes God to hear our Prayers, and bleſs his pious Deſigns: but I dare maintain at the ſame time, that we have no reaſon in the world to be in the leaſt Suſpitious of him. His Highneſs till this very day has never given any other then real Marks of his Moderation, Mildneſs and Love of the public good. During the War of the Year 1672. in the time when the Prince had many Enemies, when near three of the Provinces were already diſmember'd from the Union: When every one thought it the ſafeſt Courſe to ſhift for himſelf,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41191:6"/>
the Miſchief being without Remedy, the King of <hi>France</hi> then offer'd him the Soveraignty of the Country of <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſeveral other Places; But the generous Prince deſpiſing that Grandeur which he could not attain but by abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Unfortunate Country, choſe rather to expoſe himſelf to all the dangers that threaten the Chieftain of a ruin'd Party, then to accept of ſo tempting a Preſent from the Hand of an Enemy. His conſtancy prov'd ſucceſsful; the Factions moulder'd away to nothing; the <hi>Hollanders</hi> reſum'd freſh Courage, ſeeing themſelves Headed by the Illuſtrious Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of ſo many Hero's. Preſently the Vigilance and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his Highneſs ſet all things in Order: he waken'd <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Empire</hi> out of their Lethargic Drowſineſs; So that the <hi>French</hi> found themſelves conſtrain'd to abandon their Conqueſts in leſs time then they had ſpent in making them, notwithſtanding the rapid Inundations of their Succeſs.</p>
               <p>Since that, <hi>France</hi> has not been ſlow in taking a moſt cruel Revenge for that refuſal and Heroic Reſiſtance. She has diſmantl'd and ſackt the City of <hi>Orange,</hi> ſhe has Confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated all the Lands and Caſtles which the Prince poſſeſſes in <hi>Franche Conte,</hi> and in thoſe places which ſhe has taken from the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant.</hi> She has caus'd the Prince to beſummon'd before the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> as her <hi>Vaſſai,</hi> and Condemn'd him for default of appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and given away his Hereditary Eſtate to others. The Kings of <hi>Great Britain, Charles</hi> the II. and <hi>James</hi> the II. the one his Uncle, the other his Uncle and Father-in-Law, ſaw all theſe Injuries done him, without being in the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd. On the other ſide the Prince ſuffer'd all this with a moſt Chriſtian Patience, without making any other Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt ſo many Violences, and ſo much unworthy hard uſage, then that of <hi>God and his Right.</hi> Well knowing that Acts of Injuſtice done to great Souls, generally fall moſt heavy upon the Wrong-doers.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41191:6"/>
                  <l>For Fraud and Violence each one Surrounds</l>
                  <l>But moſtly, back from whence it came rebounds.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This Axiom has fallen out very truly. <hi>James</hi> the II. has been oblig'd to quit his Kingdom. We know not as yet what may befal <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. <hi>Felix ante Obitum Nemo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However it may come to paſs, we cannot ſufficiently admire the Mildneſs and Moderation of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> fled without being purſu'd, he eſcapes in diſguiſe, is ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped without being known. So ſoon as he is diſcover'd he has great Honour and Reſpect paid him. Commiſſioners from the Lords Spiritual and Temporal are ſent to wait upon him, who deſire him to continue in his Kingdom. He refuſes, and deſires leave to be gone: He is attended to the Sea ſide, he croſſes the Sea, and retires into <hi>France,</hi> without<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition from any Perſon whatever. Generally before ſuch Revolutions can be brought about, Slaughter, Executions and Baniſhment depopulate the Land, here was no ſuch thing to be heard of. 'Tis true the <hi>French News Books</hi> tell us of ſeveral <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fugitive Lords. But what is it drives them out of the Land; either their own pannic Fears, or the remorſe of their own Conſciences. The Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics live as much at eaſe and undiſturb'd under the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of <hi>William Henry,</hi> as under the Reign of <hi>James</hi> the II. And I dare ſay, 'twill be their own fault, if they do not enjoy a greater Tranquility then yet they do. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> are as good natur'd and compaſſionate, as they are conſtant and couragious; ſo that there needs no more then to be an Object of Pity to diſarm their Fury.</p>
               <p>Tho' we had no more then this general knowledge of the Life of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> we ought not to wonder that Heaven has ſo ſignally proſper'd his Arms, or that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have Proclaim'd both him and his Illuſtrious Conſort King and Queen. But there would be ſufficient Cauſe to be ſurpriz'd, that <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Holland</hi> either, ſhould encloſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41191:7"/>
their own Boſoms, Perſons ſo diſtruſtful, or ſuch aligning and ill minded Malecontents, that ſhould refuſe to rejoyce ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely at this Happineſs. It will hardly be believ'd there are any ſuch, at leaſt among the Proteſtants of the two Nations; and what is here ſaid is only to confirm and fortify thoſe whom the <hi>Fallacious</hi> Arguments of our Enemies, may cauſe to waver, and ſit looſe for a time. But when it ſhall be conſider'd that their moſt Serene and Sacred Majeſties, have undergon ſo many ſevere and tedions Tryals, that they have all their life time obſerv'd an equal Conduct, and that they are arriv'd to Years of mature deliberation, without derogating from themſelves, 'tis a ſign that their Souls and Minds are ſufficiently endu'd with conſtancy, and that it is impoſible they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd by Proſperity.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies nothing to ſay, that a Powerful King is always formidable to a free People; for he is only ſo, to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his Dominions. He muſt be a very Feeble Prince as well in Mind as in Body, whom the <hi>Grandees</hi> govern as they pleaſe themſelves, and according to their different In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, while they buz him in the Ears, ſometimes with the noiſe of one Faction, ſometimes of another, and make uſe of his Sacred Name as the Shuttlecock of their own Paſſions, and of the Royal Authority to the Ruin of the Subject. He muſt needs be a very Superſtitious Prince that ſuffers his Head to be fill'd with the Dotages of an Idle Monk, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he offers a pleaſing Oblation to God, in Sacrificing to the <hi>Avarice</hi> of an inſatiable Society, or by abandoning to the fury of the Souldiery the moſt ſound and ſolid Party of his Kingdom. He is but a faint and impotent Prince who is ſcar'd and frighted at the ſight of the ſlighteſt danger, and has neither Credit nor Authority to ſuppreſs the threatning diſorder. He is a Vicious, Fantaſtical, and for the leaſt Offence implacable Prince, who in the Tranſports of his Anger, or the furious Heat of his Wine, permits his hands to be clear'd of his moſt Faithful and Prudent Servants. He
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41191:7"/>
is a Prince addicted ſtrangely to his Pleaſures who ſuffers himſelf to be guided by his Confidents and his Miſtreſſes, and oppreſſes his People with exactions to gratify their Vanity. Theſe are the Princes of whom the People are to be afraid: But I would fain know what cauſe they have to fear a Wiſe, a Prudent, a Laborious, Indefatigable Prince, Religious without Superſtition, who has almoſt an equal e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for all the Societies of Proteſtantiſm, nor any bigot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hatred againſt the <hi>Roman Catholics.</hi> A daring, coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Prince, who underſtands how to ſhun Danger, and yet ready to expoſe himſelf when neceſſity requires: a Prince, ſo regular in his Manners, and in all the Conduct of his Life, that the Word <hi>Intreague</hi> is hardly known at his Court. Such a one, according to the public Voice of General Fame, is <hi>William Henry Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> now King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Prince is too Powerful, they cry, as if a Prince could be too potent, when he only makes uſe of his Authority to do good. Since the ruin of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> never was Monarch more Powerful then <hi>Charlemain,</hi> yet never did <hi>Europe</hi> Flouriſh more, never was it more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py then under his Reign, he it was that converted and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd the Government of <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Barbarian Germany;</hi> who tam'd the Pride of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and ſet bounds to the Ambition of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and by his Victories gave an Opportunity to the Chriſtians, who were retir'd to the Mountains of <hi>Biſcay</hi> and <hi>Aſturia,</hi> to enlarge their Dominions in the Plains, and by degrees to chaſe the Infidels out of <hi>Spain.</hi> He it was that reſtor'd Learning and the knowledge of the Liberal Sciences, and made the greateſt part of thoſe Laws, which to this day uphold Juſtice and good Order in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts. Nevertheleſs this Prince whoſe <hi>Empire</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended from the <hi>Brittiſh Ocean,</hi> and the Frontiers of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> to the <hi>Danaw</hi> and the <hi>Tuſcan Sea,</hi> never undertook any conſiderable Enterprize without the Advice of his <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41191:8"/>
and Counſel of his <hi>Barons,</hi> and the conſent of the Aſſembly of his Eſtates. Being fully perſwaded that the greateſt Power of a King, and the ſtrongeſt Bulwark which he can oppoſe againſt his Enemies is the Affection of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and that then they are to be govern'd with leaſt trouble, when he ſuffers Equity and Juſtice to Reign. Had the Succeſſors to <hi>Charlemain,</hi> but had wit and courage equal to Him, his <hi>Empire</hi> had not been diſmember'd into ſo many peicemeals; of which not any one having force ſufficient, to repel the Irruptions of the <hi>Northern</hi> People, <hi>Europe</hi> was ſoon after cover'd with Blood, and over-run with Ignorance and Barbariſm.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is Apparent by what has been ſaid, that a Prince is not to be fear'd by his Subjects for that reaſon only, becauſe he is Powerful: and that there is very little Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility that ever King <hi>William</hi> the II. ſhould ever make a wrong uſe of his Authority, how great ſo ever it be, that the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> and their <hi>High and Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> intruſt him withal. However, though there be nothing to be fear'd on his ſide, yet perhaps the Conſtitution of the two Eſtates which now he governs with Supream Controul, is of ſuch a Nature, that they can never remain United. Which is that which we are next to examin.</p>
               <p>It is objected that People of the ſame profeſſion rarely agree; that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> are addicted to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, that the Sea is the common Fountain and Source of their Wealth; that the two Nations have been at Wars for above theſe twenty or thirty Years, as well in the Old as New World, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all upon the ſcore of Trade: that it is very improbable they ſhould forget their Animoſities all of a ſuddain; and that each ſhould be willing to make conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on their own part, to Unite more firmly againſt their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Enemies, that the differences about the <hi>Flagg,</hi> about <hi>Fraight,</hi> the <hi>Herring-Fiſhery,</hi> and the Affairs of the <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> are too great and recent, to be ſoon made up. This
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41191:8"/>
is the Language of our Enemies, who make us ſenſible of the miſcheif they have done us, but conceal the Cauſe from us, on purpoſe to put us out of hope. But let us endeavour to find it out our ſelves, and then it will be eaſie to apply the Remedy.</p>
               <p>It is a real and undeniable Truth, that time out of mind the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Flemings</hi> have liv'd together in perfect Amity, and their <hi>Antipathy</hi> againſt the <hi>French</hi> has ſtill been the ſame, and indeed a very ſlender knowledge of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the three Nations will ſerve to convince any Man of the truth of what is here aſſerted. During the greateſt part of the Wars between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> from the Reigns of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> and <hi>Richard Ceur de Lyon,</hi> till the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the VII. and <hi>Henry</hi> the VI. the <hi>Flemings,</hi> though <hi>Vaſſals</hi> to the <hi>French,</hi> always took part with the <hi>Ilanders.</hi> They were the firſt who acknowledg'd <hi>Edward</hi> the III. King of <hi>France</hi> to the prejudice of <hi>Philip de Valois.</hi> They have ſeveral times made War with their <hi>Counts,</hi> becauſe they were too much inclined to the Intereſt of <hi>France. And though the Houſe of</hi> Burgundy <hi>was always ſo very ſparing of their Subjects, that they never kept any diſciplin'd Forces in conſtant Pay, nor Garriſons in their</hi> ſtrong Holds, <hi>believing that Subjects gently uſed, would be a ſuffieient Guard of their Country themſelves.</hi> Nevertheleſs, at the time when the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> through the Diviſions between the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> had almoſt loſt what they poſſeſt in <hi>France,</hi> they attempted to riſe in Favour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Good,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> one of the beſt Princes in the World. And the reaſon which <hi>Mezerai</hi> alledges for it is very remarkable. <hi>It was,</hi> ſays he, <hi>not only becauſe the Flme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing were at that time in a cloſe Friendſhip with</hi> England, <hi>upon the ſcore of Trade, but out of</hi> the particular hatred which they bare the <hi>French.</hi> The Cittizens of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> revolted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Charles</hi> the VII. for the ſame Reaſon, having let the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in among them. And the ſame <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> aſſures us,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41191:9"/>
that to keep in Subjection that City, which the intereſts of Commerce and reciprocal Marriages had link'd with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the King was conſtrain'd to baniſh Forty Gentlemen and Citizens whom he moſt ſuipected, and to build two <hi>Citadels</hi> beſides, the better to keep the Town in awe. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in the Year 1528. <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. having made an Agreement with <hi>Francis</hi> I. that the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould attack the <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> the V. in the <hi>Low-Countries, Mezerai</hi> obſerves, that the King perceiving, <hi>that his Subjects had an Averſion to any War againſt the Flemings, becauſe it would ruin their Trade,</hi> choſe rather to lend his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſederate Thirty Thouſand Crowns a Month; and for the renewing of Trade, negotiated a Truce between the <hi>Low-Countries, France</hi> and <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be an eaſie thing to find more examples of this Union in all Ages; but to ſpare our ſelves the trouble of ſearching ſo far off, it ſhall ſuffice to obſerve that the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces</hi> did not arrive to that high degree of Puiſſance which renders them now a Terror to their Enemies, but by the means of their Trade: nor did they begin to Flouriſh in Trade, till they had ſhaken off the Yoke of <hi>Spain,</hi> and that they came to be ſtrictly in League with <hi>England.</hi> And it was chiefly by means of the ſuccour which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſent them, that they ſupported their growing Union againſt the Formidable Forces of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> and though <hi>James</hi> the I. did not ſecond them ſo Vigorouſly, whether it were that he had too much buſineſs at home, or that the Valour and Alliances of Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſupply'd that defect; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, it may be ſaid, that if <hi>England</hi> had been their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, inſtead of being their Ally, that Valiant Prince would have found it a far more difficult task to have ſupported him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and defended his Country againſt Strangers abroad, and Factions at home.</p>
               <p>Although <hi>Great Britain</hi> no way depends upon the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> as being an <hi>Iſland</hi> that is able to ſubſiſt of its ſelf,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41191:9"/>
without borrowing from her Neighbours, yet I think ſhe has no wrong done her, in averring that the ſuccour which ſhe afforded <hi>Holland</hi> turn'd to her own profit. For as the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> utterly expell'd the <hi>Portugueſes</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of the <hi>Indies,</hi> ſo the impairing the Power of the latter did not a little contribute to aggrandize the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> and to cauſe their Trade to Flouriſh in <hi>Europe.</hi> It is alſo very probable, that if <hi>Philip</hi> the II. had not been ſo embroyl'd, as he was with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> he would have ventur'd a <hi>Second</hi> Invaſion of <hi>England.</hi> Nor would Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> been able to have reform'd and govern'd her Kingdom ſo peaceably as ſhe did, after the Deſtruction of the Invincible <hi>Armada:</hi> and indeed never was the Trade of the <hi>Iſland</hi> in a more flouriſhing condition then under the Reign of that Queen. <hi>James</hi> the I. confirm'd the Alliance and found the benefit of it as long as he liv'd: And <hi>Charles</hi> the I. was ſo far from being ignorant of how great conſequence it was for the two Nations to continue inſeparably United, that he gave one of his Daughters to <hi>William</hi> the II. Father to his preſent Majeſty. After all, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have experienc'd the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of having good Neighbours: and indeed, according to all outward Appearances, had there been no <hi>Hollanders,</hi> nor any Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in the World, the Religion, Laws and Liberties would have run a great hazard of being utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aboliſh'd; or at leaſt the ſtrugling for them would have coſt a vaſt Effuſion of Blood.</p>
               <p>The firſt that broke the happy Union of theſe two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper Cromwel,</hi> out of his hatred to the Houſe of the <hi>Stewarts.</hi> The two Brothers, Sons of <hi>Charles</hi> the I. during their Exile, ſuffer'd their heads to be intoxicated with a neceſſity of Abſolute Power, looking upon it as the only Remedy to prevent the frequent Revolutions in <hi>England.</hi> Now when this Fancy had taken deep root, it was eaſie to perſwade them that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, or New up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart Opinions, as the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> call them, nouriſh in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41191:10"/>
People this ſame Spirit of change and inconſtancy: For that they who will be troubling their heads to examine whether their Biſhops and Paſtors do not delude and miſlead them, will as ſoon take the ſame Liberty to enquire into the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Kings; and will not ſuffer them to invade their Priviledges, nor to violate the Conditions of their Coronation-Oath. That the only means to bring about their ends upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to free the Crown from depending upon <hi>Parliaments,</hi> was to introduce Popery by degrees into the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> for that under pretence of thoſe inſenſible changes which Religion would ſuffer, it would be eaſie to alter the Laws and Form of the Government.</p>
               <p>For the Execution of this Deſign it was thought expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, or rather neceſſary. 1. To cut off all the moſt ſhrew'd and Politic Head-peices in the Nation, under va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Colours and Pretences. 2. To deprive the great Cities one after another of their Charters; and ever and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to break in upon the Priviledges of the Clergy, Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and People. 3. To be always engag'd in ſome Foreign War; thereby to have a ſpecious occaſion to keep up a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Force, and ſet up a Shambles to conſume and waſte away the moſt ſtout and daring of the Nobility and Gentry; and to accuſtom the Subject to new and frequent Taxes, and drain their Purſes. 4. To ſow Jealouſies between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> on purpoſe to make uſe of one of the Nations to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Liberties of the other. 5. To foment the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to multiply their Sects, and keep them in a kind of Equality, by favouring ſometimes one, and ſometimes the other, to the end that after ſeveral Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Parliament might be conſtrain'd to come to a U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Toleration, which would ſoon open a door to let in Popery into the Government. 6. That while the deſign was carrying on to amuſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with a Foreign War, and at the ſame time their Deſtruction was contriving at home, the main thing to be conſider'd was, whether to cuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41191:10"/>
with <hi>France</hi> or the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces. France</hi> was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>Roman Catholic,</hi> and the place where Arbitrary Power Reign'd in Triumph. If you lead the <hi>Engliſh</hi> thither, 'tis true you gratify'd their natural Inclination, but augmented their deteſtation of Popery and Slavery. And then it was to enfeeble a Power, by means of which they were to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh blind Obedience in the Iſland. Therefore it was concluded that all the Force of the three Kingdoms ſhould be turn'd upon <hi>Holland;</hi> for indeed there lay all the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Malice. Reformation was the prevailing Religion of thoſe Fortunate Provinces; Liberty was the Pillar that ſupported them. They had been a long time the Sanctuary of Unfortunate Fugitives and Exiles. Moreover it was foreſeen that while they enclos'd within their own Boſom the two next Heirs of the Crown, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abus'd and oppreſs'd would not fail to repair to them. Therefore there was no more to be done but abſolutely to determin; <hi>that Carthage was to be utterly deſtroy'd.</hi> We muſt acknowledge that never was any Project better laid; but unfortunately for the Contrivers; the Impatience of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the Courage, Union and Piety of the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> ſpoil'd all. Their Royal Highneſſes refuſe their Conſent to repeal the Teſts; King <hi>James</hi> is Angry, puſhes on things to extremity, and counterfeits a Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> redouble their Murmurs; the Prince Arms without making any Noiſe, Lands in <hi>England,</hi> where all give way, the Generality joyn with him, while the King abandons all at once both his Kingdom and his Vain En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes. But that I may no longer tarry upon a Subject that has been now the occaſion of ſo much Writing, and which is now, God be thanked, quite out of Seaſon, I ſhall apply my ſelf at preſent to obſerve by what Artifices the Court of <hi>England</hi> Labour'd to render the War againſt the <hi>Hollanders</hi> acceptable to the People. This is that which moſt peculiarly was my Aim, and upon which I am apt to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41191:11"/>
believe the Public has not ſeen any Reflections eſpecially in our Language.</p>
               <p>The Deſigns of Princes are manag'd at a diſtance, and perhaps it may not be thought an ill Conjecture, ſhould I preſume to ſay that the ſecret Motive which induc'd the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of the <hi>Eaſt Indie</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Companies was to leſſen the Power of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and to ſerve for a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to find an occaſion of a Quarrel, when it ſhould be thought convenient. At leaſt, there are ſeveral Perſons who openly maintain that thoſe Societies are meer <hi>Monopolies,</hi> more fit to ruine the Trade of a great Kingdom, then to advance it. However it be, 'tis probable that the Court flatter'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with the hopes of rendring them abſolute Maſters of the Sea and Navigation, and giving them the poſſeſſion of thoſe Wealthy Countries which the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> are Maſters of in the <hi>Eaſt Indies.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, they that lookt upon things with a clear ſight, perceiv'd that it was only a Bait; but yet as evident as it was, the common People ſwallow'd it down. <hi>Charles</hi> the II. and the D. of <hi>York</hi> were then * Members of the<note place="margin">1664.</note> Church of <hi>England,</hi> and no body ſo much as dreamt at that time, that they were then forming a reſolution to betray the Party. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are ſo eaſie of belief, that if <hi>James</hi> the II. had not bethought himſelf, after the Death of his Brother, to Publiſh a Writing under his Brother's Hand, which he aſſur'd the World contain'd the Real Profeſſion of his Faith, no body would ever have imagin'd that a Perſon of his ſublime Wit, and ſo great a Monarch could have perſever'd in his Hypocriſie till Death: and it is thought even to this day, that he was either of the Reformed Religion, or that he had none at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>The Advantages which the Tyrant <hi>Cromwell,</hi> one of the greateſt Captains of the Age, had obtain'd over the <hi>Hollanders</hi> from the Year 1651. to 1654. made the common People of <hi>England</hi> look upon the Conqueſt of <hi>Holland</hi> as an eaſie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41191:11"/>
undertaking. They imagin'd, ſeeing that juſt after the Concluſion of a Civil War, under a Uſurper not well ſettl'd, and at a time when the Land was all embroyl'd with Factions, they had conſtrain'd their Enemies to a diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Peace, that they ſhould reduce them much lower, ſhould they Attack them, being well United, with all their Forces, under their lawful Prince. <hi>France</hi> promis'd to Aſſiſt them privately, to amuſe the <hi>Hollanders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> with hopes of feigned Succour, and to powre in upon them, ſo ſoon as ſhe ſhould find it proper. All the World knows the Succeſs of that War, which laſted above three Years; during which time the two Nations Experienc'd what judicious Hiſtorians have already obſerv'd; that they could not vanquiſh one another, being very near of equal ſtrength at Sea; and therefore that their Engagements would only contribute to their Mutual Ruine.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1672. <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. undertook the Conqueſt of <hi>Holland</hi> with more Succeſs then <hi>Charles</hi> II. had done eight Years before. At what time the Court of <hi>England</hi> believing the <hi>Hollanders</hi> loſt beyond recovery, at the beginning of the firſt Campagne openly joyn'd with <hi>France.</hi> And indeed there had been an end of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> had the <hi>Engliſh</hi> continu'd the War with that Vigor as they did in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1665. But that quickſighted Nation perceiving that the Religion and Liberties of their Neighbours were more aim'd at, then their Trade and Riches, repreſented to their King that there was nothing to be gain'd by that War but blows, and that the <hi>French</hi> only ſought to amuſe them till he made himſelf Maſter of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi> Theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were laid before the King with ſo much ſtrength of Argument; and the Parliaments refus'd with ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy thoſe Aids which the King ſtood in need of to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the War, that King <hi>Charles</hi> found himſelf conſtrain'd to accept of thoſe Propoſals which were made him by the States, and the Treaty was concluded at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 19.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41191:12"/>
of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1674. And whatever endeavours the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have ſince us'd they could never engage their Subjects in an open and formal War with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is eaſie to deduce ſeveral Conſequences from this piece of ſtory, which utterly diſſipate thoſe vain Jealouſies that the Enemies of the two Nations would fain create between them, under pretence of Trade. 1. The Firſt is that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> have no natural Antipathy one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other; and that their Three laſt Wars were only the Effect of an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> Revenge, who labour'd the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Royal Family; and of two Kings their Conceal'd Enemies, who had ſworn the utter Extirpation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, their Priviledges and Liberties. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is that Commerce is ſo far from being a lawful Cauſe of the difference between the two Nations, that on the contrary it ought to incline them to a ſtricter Union, if they underſtand their own Intereſts, ſince their Trade then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways flouriſh'd moſt when there was the ſtricteſt Amity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. 3. The Third is that, they ought to take a more then ordinary care how they Engage in a War one againſt the other, well knowing that in all their Sea En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, the Advantages on both ſides have been very little different, or rather that they have come off with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual loſſes, and that Strangers taking the real Advantages of their Quarrels are become their Rivals in Navigation. <hi>Hambrough</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Hanſe-Towns,</hi> the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> for the moſt part now take in thoſe Freights, by which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> before gain'd ſo much profit, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs'd to themſelves a great part of the Trade of the <hi>Baltic</hi> Sea. The <hi>French</hi> who ſince the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. had not ſo much as one Ship that belong'd to the King, have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd ſeveral Territories in <hi>America,</hi> and are now Labouring to get Footing in the <hi>Indies,</hi> by that Alliance which they have contracted with the King of <hi>Siam;</hi> ſet forth great Fleets, and peſter the Sea with Pyrates. All which came to paſs, while
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41191:12"/>
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> were buſily imploy'd in ruining one another. So that if three of their Wars have ſo ſenſibly abated their Trade to ſuch a degree; the Fourth, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the preſent Union of the Two Nations, would be the Effect of an Irreconcileable Hatred, would prove their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruin, by Tranſlating to their Neighbours all the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which the two Nations receive by their Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
               <p>As for what concerns their Quarrels about loaring the Flag, Freights, and the Herring-Fiſhery, they are not worth the trouble of any farther diſcourſe; and to bury them in <hi>Oblivion,</hi> there needs no more then to keep cloſe to the Peace of <hi>Breda</hi> in the Year 1667. The differences between the two <hi>Eaſt India Companies</hi> ſeem more conſiderable, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs if Men would but rightly underſtand one another, it might be eaſie to remove this Stumbling-block, either by Incorporating altogether, or by ſome other way which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident deliberation might ſoon find out.</p>
               <p>The Third Objection falls of it ſelf, after what has been ſaid to refute the Second. The Intereſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> inclining them to the continuance of their Union, and to contribute their utmoſt to their mutual Proſperity, there would never be any Jealouſie between the two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, unleſs they lent their Ears to the ſeducing Fallacies of their Enemies; and by conſequence their King and their Governour would have no occaſion to Invade their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. Beſides that we are confidently aſſur'd that he will never endeavour it, but on the other ſide will uſe all his endeavours to prevent any difference between the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are equally dear to him. But ſuppoſing that we were not ſo certain as we are of the mildneſs and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his preſent Majeſty; at leaſt we dare not queſtion but that he is a Perſon of Honour and a Valiant Prince, and that he has a High Eſteem for true Glory. If he has won Battles, if he has taken ſtrong Towns, if he has made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41191:13"/>
Conqueſts, he is only beholding for all this to the Bleſſing of God, to his Valour, and the exact Diſcipline which he obſerves in his Armies, and the Love which his Souldiers have for him. He was never known to purchaſe ſtrong Holds, to corrupt Governours, nor to aggrandize himſelf by fowl and treacherous means; If ſeveral <hi>French</hi> Officers have Liſted themſelves in his Service, it was the Catholic Zeal which expell'd them their Country, and the Reputation of ſo great a Captain, which made them eager to ſerve under his Command. How can it be imagin'd, that a Prince, who next to God is beholding for his high advancement, only to the largeneſs of his Soul, and the greatneſs of his Courage, to the Wiſdom of his Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and the Love of his People: A Prince, that has ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd ſo long, and with a Patience unimitable, the wrongs that have been done him; who never took up Arms in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of his own Intereſts, but to deliver an Oppreſs'd Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that implor'd his Aid: How, I ſay, can it be conceiv'd, that it ſhould ever come into ſuch a Princes thoughts by indirect ways to deſtroy that Liberty, which he adventur'd to reſtore with the hazard of his Blood and Life: or that he would go about, for an Airy Authority, to looſe that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Glory which he has acquired; Or that while he Reigns as he does, in the Hearts of his Subjects and Allies, he ſhould rather chooſe to draw upon himſelf the Hatred of the One and the Indignation of the Other, rather then peaceably to enjoy the Fruit of his Labours.</p>
               <p>If on the one fide Honour engages his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> to preſerve the Priviledges of his Subjects, as his own Handy-work, and to maintain the Liberty of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> his Fellow-Citizens, it inclines him on the other ſide to exterminate Tyranny. We know it Triumphs in <hi>France</hi> with an unlimited Power, and that it is there, as it were in the Center. Nor are we ignorant of the heinous Injuries which <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has offer'd to <hi>William</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41191:13"/>
the III. when he was only Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Governour and <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough of themſelves to engage in a War with the <hi>French;</hi> and ſeveral Hiſtorians have obſerv'd that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give Money with a more willing Heart, then when they are ask'd to contribute toward the Expences of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition. Beſides they well underſtand, that <hi>Cromwels</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil War. The Evil Deſigns of their two laſt Kings, their Inteſtine Diſcords, their Engagements againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> in a word all that themſelves and their Brethren have ſuffer'd for this laſt near half an Age together, has been only the Effect of the Intreagues of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> of the two Cardinals and the Jeſuits. Nor have the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> leſs Cauſe to complain. Not to mention the unjuſt Invaſion in 1672. for which all the Subtlety of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth's Counſel, could never alledge any other well grounded Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then the favourable Opportunity to Conquer thoſe Rich Provinces, through the Cowardiſe, ſloath and want of Intelligence in thoſe that manag'd Affairs at that time; were there nothing elſe but the Violences and Cruelties which the <hi>French</hi> King and his Miniſters have Committed within theſe Nine or Ten Years upon the Subjects of the <hi>States General,</hi> their Ships Embargo'd, their Goods Confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, their Seamen Impriſon'd, conſtrain'd to change their Religion, to ſerve againſt their own Country, or to undergo the Puniſhment of the Gallies; the prodigious Number of Merchants Ships which their Privateers have taken; their Villages and Towns laid in Aſhes, and all this in time of Peace, and without the leaſt appearance of Juſtice; I dare be bold to ſay, that their <hi>High and Mightineſſes</hi> muſt have Hearts of Steel to be inſenſible of theſe Recent Outrages; and that all the Offers and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations that <hi>France</hi> can make, are not ſufficient to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41191:14"/>But ſome will ſay, it is the Intereſt of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> to continue in Peace, and the States never had a fairer opportunity to obtain from <hi>France</hi> whatever they ſhall judge requiſite for the ſecurity of their Subjects and their Trade. I acknowledge it: But who ſhall be <hi>Guarantee</hi> for the Obſervation of the Treaty which is to be made with <hi>France?</hi> Certainly neither <hi>England,</hi> nor the <hi>Empire.</hi> Is it prudence to confide in thoſe Perſons who have a thouſand times deceiv'd us, who never keep their word any longer, then ſincerity agrees with their Ambitious Deſires, and their Intereſts: who make a ſport of their Promiſes, Oaths, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, and moſt ſolemn Edicts, who are equally Treacherous to Friends and Enemies, Subjects and Allies? True it is that Peace is very deſireable; but not a Peace of ſix Months or a Year, but a firm, ſtable and perpetual Peace; or at leaſt ſuch a Peace as ſhall laſt as long as we live. 'Tis alſo as true that it is the Intereſt of Common-wealths rather to preſerve themſelves in the Condition they are in, then to make new Conqueſts. But when we have Neighbours Potent, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and ſuch as ſeek to aggrandize themſelves by all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of means, right or wrong, they have no other way to ſecure themſelves from their unlookt for Invaſions, then to take advantage of the firſt opportunity that preſents it ſelf to pull down their Power, and to reduce them to ſuch a Condition that they be no longer able to do any more Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
               <p>This Happy Opportunity is now come: <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> have now <hi>William</hi> the III. for their Sovereign and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. The whole Body of <hi>Germany</hi> moves toward Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. The <hi>French</hi> themſelves pant after their deliverance; the Perſecuted <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> are not the only Male Contents of that Kingdom. The Clergy, the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and People, all Orders of the Kingdom groan under the Tyranny of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and only wait for a Chieftain to deliver them from Slavery. This is a truth not to be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41191:14"/>
and to convince the Public, there needs no more for any Man to do, then to caſt his Eyes upon the general Cauſes of the Diſcontents of the <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No Country is more Fruitful, no Climate more tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ſerene then theirs, no Inhabitants more Civil or more Humane, then thoſe of this Kingdom. You would ſay, it was a Country made on purpoſe to be the Habitation of Good and Vertuous People, and a Paradiſe upon Earth. <hi>But as it is a Country Rich and Fertile, and as the People are extreamly humble and ſubmiſſive, they are overwhelm'd with all ſorts of exactions, inſomuch that their Plenty becomes their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and their Obedience makes their Oppreſſions more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To reduce a free and Warlike People into ſo rigorous a Servitude requir'd a long time, and a world of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. It was requiſite to raviſh from the Clergy their Rights, to deprive the Nobility of their Priviledges, and to invade the Liberties of the People. 'Tis well known that the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church has bred up and foſter'd in her Boſom the greateſt Luminaries in <hi>Europe;</hi> that ſhe has had in all Ages Holy Biſhops, who have oppos'd the Uſurpations of the Popes, who have publicly rebuk'd the Vices of the Grandees, and have openly withſtood the Tyranny of Princes. The Inferior Clergy were ſolely under the Juriſdiction of their Prelates, their provincial and national Synods. At this day they are expos'd to the Mercy of the Court and the Fury of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> not only in civil Cauſes, but alſo in what concerns their Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline and Religion. A world of Formalities, a world of Aſſemblies, but no appeal againſt a Letter under the Privy Signet.</p>
               <p>We alſo know what has formerly been the Power of the Nobility: without their Conſent, neither Peace could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, nor War undertaken, nor any Leagues offenſive or defenſive could be made. Offices of public Truſt, which are now put to Sale, the Prey of Uſurpers in Confederacy, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41191:15"/>
Hunger-ſtarv'd Commiſſaries: Military Imployments which are beſtowed for the moſt part upon Souldiers of Fortune, or the Lacqueys of Favourites. Benefices, which are now at the abſolute diſpoſal of the Kings Confeſſor, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Conſcience or the Jeſuits; All Penſions, all Civil or<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Eccleſiaſtical Dignities, all conſiderable Employments were as it were Portions for the Younger Sons of Noble Families, and afforded them Means to ſupport the luſtre of their Houſe. Whereas now we ſee the Nobility without Eſtates, and ill Educated, through Poverty or want of Education ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the meaneſt of Drudgeries. Formerly, when a Lord was diſguſted with the Court, he retir'd to his Caſtle, where he liv'd like a petty Soveraign, no Man daring to come to trouble his Repoſe. But thoſe happy days are paſt; Now they muſt eat their Bread in the train of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, make their applications to ſuch as have only their Vices or their Intreagues to favour them; and inſtead of that noble Fireceneſs ſo well becoming thoſe whom Birth, Knowledge and Vertue have rais'd above the Common Sort, they muſt now put on the Countenances of Slaves and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants upon the approach of a Beggar in Rich Apparel, a Commiſſary of the Treaſury, or a Jeſuit of the Court.</p>
               <p>As for the People, their miſery is ſo great, as would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a ſhowr of Bloody Tears to deplore it, and a Graving Tool of Iron to deſcribe it, ſo that I have often queſtion'd whether Poſterity would give credit to what a thouſand Teſtimonies have both ſeen and try'd themſelves; and which they can never expreſs but in a Language far ſhort of the Truth. Who would believe that a People Laborious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Active, Sober, Induſtrious, that inhabits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Country <hi>Fertil</hi> in Corn, abounding in Wine, in Cattel, in Paſturage, in Oyl, in Salt, in all ſorts of Fruits; a Country water'd with large Rivers; to the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> waſh'd by the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and to the <hi>South</hi> by the <hi>Mediterranean Sea,</hi> as if Nature, not content with the peculiar Wealth ſhe has beſtow'd upon it, deſign'd to furniſh
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41191:15"/>
it with all that Foreign <hi>Climates</hi> have in particular. I ſay who would believe that a People thus endow'd in the midſt of a ſoil abounding with Milk and Honey, ſhould be forc'd to dwell in Straw Huts, and to be reduc'd to Beggary. Who would believe that there ſhould be nothing to be ſeen but Palaces demoliſh'd and ruin'd Houſes in a Kingdom where no Enemy has been ravaging for theſe two or three Ages to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. That a Country Husband man, after he has till'd his own Lands, and reap'd the Harveſt ſhould have nothing but a little Rye, Barley or Cheſt-nuts to eat, or the ſqueezings of the Lees of the Grape mixed with Water, or Water it ſelf to drink. For the Collector of the Kings duties, has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoil'd him of his Wheat, his Wine and his Oyl, leaving him hardly wherewithal to ſow his Land next Year, and pay his Tenths. Beſides that the Land is over and above charg'd with duties for goods brought in and going forth, Cuſtoms and other exceſſive Taxes, and to compleat the total con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming of what the Collectors could not carry away, the Souldiers run from <hi>Province</hi> to <hi>Province</hi> trampling the poor People under foot.</p>
               <p>Strangers wonder at the vaſt Number of Souldiers, that <hi>France</hi> keeps up in pay. But this does not come to paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Kingdom is better Peopl'd then other Countries. You ſhall travel ſeveral Leagues together, through moſt <hi>fertile</hi> Champaign Countries, and hardly meet with one poor miſerable Cottage; whereas the very Merſhes, and Sands of <hi>Holland</hi> ſeem to be but one Great and Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent City. But the reaſon is, for that being Born where only the King, the Favourites of the Wealthy, and the Souldiers can live, the reſt muſt either carry a Muſquet or ſtarve.</p>
               <p>In all other Countries the Great Cities enjoy conſiderable Priviledges, hold General Aſſemblies compoſed of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, the Clergy and the third Eſtate, where they conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of what concerns the public good, to prevent the indiſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41191:16"/>
of bad Counſellers from putting the Kingdom in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion, and the hungry Courtiers from inriching themſelves with the ſweat of the People. 'Tis not ſo in <hi>France; Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux, Marſeilles, Toulouſe, La Rochelle, Niſmes, Montauban,</hi> &amp;c. have all loſt their <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> and are curb'd and kept in awe by Citadels and ſtrong Garriſons. The King keeps his Court but ſeldom in <hi>Paris,</hi> to leſſen the Power of that Proud City. All the reſt of the Cities are ſo poor, that <hi>Grenoble,</hi> one of the moſt Flouriſhing and Capital of the <hi>Dauphinate,</hi> the Seat of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of that <hi>Province,</hi> is not able to raiſe Money to reſtrain within it's Channel a ſmall River, that overflows the Country and many times threatens the City with a deſtructive deluge. The <hi>Parliaments,</hi> more eſpecially that of <hi>Paris,</hi> had reſerv'd to themſelves a right to examine the Edicts and Decrees of their Prince. And if they found any thing fit to be excepted againſt, they humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented their exceptions to his Majeſty, as they did to <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. when he was deſigning to recal the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and their remonſtrances were frequently of that force as to cancel an Edict, otherwiſe they allow'd and confirm'd it. But they have Puniſh'd with ſo much rigor and cruelty ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, who in the late troubles, during the Minority of the King, gave proof of their conſtancy and zeal for the public good, that at this day no Body dares ſo much as open their mouths. Nor do they now make uſe of the Word <hi>d'Enteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> which properly ſignifies to give the force of a Law to a Declaration of the Prince; ſo that the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> for fear of joſtling the <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> of their <hi>Invincible Monarch,</hi> barely write down, that they have read ſuch or ſuch an Edict of the King, and that they have <hi>Verify'd</hi> it; that is, they have acknowledg'd it to be his Majeſties Act and Deed. After which, his moſt humble Slaves have not a Word more to ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41191:16"/>I will not here ſpeak of that ſame tedious and barbarous Perſecution of the <hi>Reformed,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> though that Party was very conſiderable in the Kingdom; as well for that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors have made very large Deſcriptions of it, as for that it is not convenient to meddle with Particular dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in a diſcourſe that relates only to the public Intereſt. I ſhall only obſerve that Religion, which is the General Pretence laid hold of to cauſe the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe violent Proceedings, is not the real cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and that it is not out of any zeal for the Glory of God, that thoſe poor People are depriv'd of their Relations and Friends, and of their fellow Citizens, and that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and ruin their Trade. It may be that the King is over perſwaded that his conſcience obliges him to exterminate Hereſy. But he is a good natur'd Prince, naturally not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to cruelty: yet when he is made believe that he offers an oblation to God, in Sacrificing to his vengeance thoſe that worſhip him after a manner different from ours, it is enough to overcome a good diſpoſition, and puſh on zeal even to fury. But as for his Counſellers they are too ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to the World, to make any doubt whether Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience or Religion are the Motives that ſpur them on to Act. 'Tis certain they are not; and therefore we muſt ſeek out for others; and I think I have call'd to mind ſome of them. The firſt is, the hatred of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> againſt all thoſe that are not of their Opinion. For Opinion is the Queen of the World. And therefore they who would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand others, uſe all their endeavours to make thoſe whom they labour to bring under Subjection to admit of their Maxims, chiefly thoſe that relate to Philoſophy, Divinity and Morality. The <hi>Grandees</hi> can eaſily rid themſelves of a few Private Perſons by the way of Calumny, or by bringing them into trouble; but to deſtroy a numerous Body, that continually raiſes up freſh Enemies, there is no way but to proceed by open force. The <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> being the moſt Rigid
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41191:17"/>
of all the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, always found the <hi>Reformed</hi> to be Oppoſers of their deſigns. Nor were the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> who accus'd theſe Fathers for being the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſtian Morality, leſs odious to them. But the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety being more Powerful then both theſe, brought about their ends by a Perſecution of above Forty Years. In the firſt Place they put in practice Proceſſes and brangling Suits, Knavery and Impoſture, of which they made uſe againſt thoſe that eſcap'd their fury, by flying for Sanctuary into Foreign Countries.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Motive to Perſecution is the Avarice of the Society, which appear'd, by the Benefices and Eſtates of the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> confiſcated, which the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd to be given to themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Politicians alſo give us ſome Reaſons for theſe <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> they ſay, that the King is a great Lover of Glory, and makes it a point of Honour to deſtroy a Religion, which his Predeceſſors would have eradicated, but could not. They add, that the Victories he has gain'd, and the Progreſs he has made, through the Diviſions of the <hi>Neighbouring Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and by other Stratagems have puft him up to believe that he is able to execute whatever he undertakes: and that it is as eaſie for him to force his Subjects to change their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, as to win the ſtrong holds of his Enemies. Others there are who will have it, that the Court has Sacrific'd the Reformed to the Ghoſts of the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> and that to procure the condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention of the <hi>Pope</hi> that the Diſciples of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> might be perſecuted, and the Canonical Elections aboliſh'd in theſe Churches where they were preſerv'd, they bethought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of oppreſſing the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> which has been always a great Mark of <hi>Catholiciſm.</hi> Others hold, that it was the deſign of the Miniſters of State, and ſuperntendants to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves with the ſpoils of thoſe that fled, to defray the expences of the War, and pay off the half famiſh'd Souldiers: perſwading the King that a ſmall number of poor
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41191:17"/>
People by leaving his Kingdom, did but diſcharge it of an unprofitable Burthen. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> there are ſome, that maintain that though there were no ſuch probable reaſons to be given, there would be cauſe enough to believe, that in a Court, like that of <hi>France,</hi> Religion is uſually the Motive leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd.</p>
               <p>However it be, moſt evident it is, that both <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> are Baniſh'd alike; that Religious Houſes are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, as well as the Reformed Churches, that Monaſteries are ſack'd and deſtroy'd as well as Temples, and that they make War with the ſame violence upon thoſe that adhere to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as upon thoſe that ſide with <hi>Calvin.</hi> This I ſay, is an evident ſign that it is not the Doctrine of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church,</hi> but <hi>Jeſuitiſm,</hi> which is the immediate Incentive to all theſe Cruelties. That is to ſay, that the Politcs of <hi>Matchiavel;</hi> the thirſt of Rule, and to eſtabliſh their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at any rate whatever, to ruin thoſe by all manner of ways that oppoſe them, and to diſpoſe abſolutely of the Bodys, Eſtates and Conſciences of the People carry them to theſe Courſes.</p>
               <p>Whence it follows, that all the <hi>French Roman Catholics</hi> or others, ought to look upon theſe Perſecutions. 1. As At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts againſt the Public Faith, as being contrary to the Edicts of <hi>Nantes</hi> and <hi>Niſmes,</hi> confirm'd to outward Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance by all the Declarations publiſh'd againſt the Reformed; and to a Decree of Council by which the King forbids the diſturbance of ſuch as ſhould have ſubſcrib'd the Formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, and promiſes the ſame Uſage to the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> as to the <hi>Moliniſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Perſecutions ranverſe the Foundations of public Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and introduce the Inquiſition. 'Tis well known that the Queſtions about Predeſtination and Grace are very nice and thorny; and how eaſie a thing it is, whatever the receiv'd opinion may be, to give a Heretical Sence to inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Propoſitions: ſo that if there be any that bear malice to a Learned Man, or that he ſhall be ſo unfortunate as to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41191:18"/>
diſpleaſe the Society, then is he loſt for ever; ſince there is nothing more eaſie then to forge an imaginary Hereſie out of a Metaphyſical Controverſie.</p>
               <p>3. The Perſecutions of the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> lay a ſnare for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, which they are not well able to be aware of. For ſhould the Diſputes happen to be about Predeſtination or Grace, the Myſteries of the Holy Trinity, the Incarnation, the free Satisfaction of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> If what we ought to believe were clearly taught in Scripture, or had been decided in a General Council according to the Principles receiv'd among the Chriſtians, the Oppoſers would be treated as Heretics. But neither <hi>Pelagius,</hi> nor St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> were ever condemn'd by the Univerſal Church, and though the Body of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church agree with the <hi>Semipelagians;</hi> nevertheleſs, if the Diſciples of <hi>Molinus,</hi> would but ſpeak candidly, they muſt acknowledge that the contrary Doctrin has always been tolerated. The Hereſie of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is a <hi>Chimera, Godeſcale</hi> was Perſecuted by the Faction of the two <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Rabanus Maurus</hi> of <hi>Mayence,</hi> and <hi>Hincmar</hi> of <hi>Rheims.</hi> The greateſt part of the Prelates and Learned Men of <hi>Germany</hi> undertook the Defence of his Doctrin; Nevertheleſs <hi>Semipelagianiſm</hi> was never liſted in the Number of Errors againſt the Faith, but got great footing afterwards in the <hi>Weſt.</hi> On the other ſide, the Writings of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and his Diſciples, St. <hi>Proſper,</hi> St. <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory. Tho. Aquinas,</hi> and an Infinite Number of others have been approv'd, receiv'd and reſpected by all the Church: And there needs no more then to read and underſtand them, to ſee then <hi>Janſenius</hi> has taught nothing but what other Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Doctors taught before him. How is it then poſſible<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that a Divine, who ſhall read the Books of the Holy Fathers who ſhall reverence them as Saints, who ſhall look upon them as Teſtimonies to confirm the Doctrin of the Ages they liv'd in; how is it poſſible, I ſay, but that he muſt either iump with them in opinion, or condemn thoſe that follow
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41191:18"/>
them; conſequently how can he avoid being either a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic or a Favourer of Heretics?</p>
               <p>4. Theſe Perſecutions are contrary to the Law of Nature and Nations. The Law of Nature permits every one to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his own Eſtate and his Life by all the lawful ways that may be, and ordains as to others, that we ſhould deal by them, as we would they ſhould deal by us. So that this Law is quite overturn'd in ſuch Places, where the Eſtate, Life and Honour of ſeveral Perſons depend upon the Fancy of a ſingle Perſon, and where the Innocent are oppreſs'd by a violent Faction, and by a Power uſurp'd and purely Arbitrary, without any regard to the Law. By vertue of which Law of Nations, the Contracts of Superiour to Inferiour, or of equal to equal, remain immoveable. The conſequence of which is, that every Man may live without diſturbance in his own Houſe, and enjoy his Eſtate in Tranquility, provided he behave himſelf peaceably toward the Government, and Act nothing contrary to the Laws, either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical. Now the Proteſtant Religion having been eſtabliſh'd in <hi>France</hi> by Solemn Edicts, and ſeeing that the Doctrin of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was never yet Condemn'd by any Council, it is moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that the Perſecution of the Subjects for one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two Beliefs, is a violation of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Nations, before an Aſſembly of Eſtates have revok'd thoſe Edicts, or a National Synod have rejected the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin.</p>
               <p>If then all the Facts that have been hither to alledg'd are certain; if it be true that the Clergy have been deſpoil'd of their Libertys, the Nobility of their Employments and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, the People of their Subſiſtance. If it be true, that <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Miniſters, Catholics</hi> and <hi>Reformed</hi> have been and ſtill are Perſecuted under the ſpecious Colour of Religion, againſt Public Faith and Aſſurances, againſt Eſtabliſh'd Laws and Irrevocable Edicts; and againſt the Law of Nature and of Nations; If it be true, that it is impoſſible for any <hi>French</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41191:19"/>
Divine or Learned Man to write according to his Conſcience, even in reference to thoſe things which the <hi>Gallican Church,</hi> has left undecided. If it be true, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have a deſign in hand to extirpate their Enemies by all manner of ways which they ſhall deem proper, and that they are ſo much Maſters of the Kings Favour, that they can but only ask and have, but that all good Men, that all <hi>France,</hi> and all <hi>Europe</hi> betake themſelves to their Arms to exterminate this Impious Society, which permits Murder, Robbery, Whoredom and all Sorts of Vices: that they ſet up the Standard, not againſt the King and Kingdom, but to deliver his moſt Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty from his wicked Counſellers, that fill the Churches and Monaſteries with falſe Paſtors and Intruders, that exclude the Nobility from their Employments, and beſtow them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own Creatures, that fat themſelves with the Blood of the People and enrich themſelves with the Confiſcate E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Innocent.</p>
               <p>Nor would it be a Bloody War, but an eaſie Victory for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> under the lucky <hi>Auſpices</hi> of their Prince; or rather an Extirpation of Tyranny and the Delivery of an unhappy People, worthy of a better Fate, reſolv'd on by both Nations, to the end that the Deliverer of <hi>England,</hi> may be no leſs celebrated for ſetting <hi>France</hi> at Liberty. More eſpecially while the <hi>French,</hi> thus lying under the ſmart of their Provocations, are thus favourably diſpos'd to Aſſiſt the Enterpriſes of their Avenger.</p>
               <p>But ſhould this come to paſs, cry ſome; in regard the War could not be long, and that the ſucceſs would be almoſt unqueſtionable; This, they cry, would be ſtill to make <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> more puiſſant and more formidable. And then they come in with their Proverbs, and ſay, 'tis hard for Mortal Man to preſerve his Vertue from Temptation in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing Proſperity. And let the Kings Intentions, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be never ſo ſincere and upright, who ſhall aſſure us of the vertue and honeſty of his Counſellers? This looks like a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41191:19"/>
Mans tormenting himſelf for recreations ſake; or like his framing <hi>Chimeras</hi> to combat the ſhadows of his own fancy. An Ordinary Perſon; that has but common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Prudence, never changes upon the leaſt puff of Wind; but when he has all his Life long obſerv'd certain Maxims of Honeſty, which have gain'd him a reſpect in the World, and are conformable to the Dictates of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it is the leaſt of his thoughts to depart from them, for that he underſtands that Levity is a mark of weakneſs of mind and want of wit, and that nothing is more diſpleaſing to God then Inconſtancy and Breach of Word. Much leſs can we believe that a Prince, of a clear underſtanding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and couragious, could ever be capable of change; or that he would go about to tarniſh his Honour, diſturb his own repoſe, or to render himſelf unacceptable to God, of whoſe Bleſſings at preſent he is ſo well aſſur'd. Beſides that, Courtiers, when they perceive their Maſter to be a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon accompliſh'd in vertue, are wary how they let him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Irregularities of their inclinations, but rather make it their Study to ſhew themſelves conformable to his diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They are cautious of giving him bad Council for fear of incurring his diſpleaſure. They will rather on the contrary Study to become vertuous or at leaſt to ſeem ſo. Beſides the Counſellers of King <hi>William</hi> are no more to be fear'd, then the King himſelf. Their modeſty will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to give the World a lively Portraiture of their vertues, and therefore it will ſuffice to obſerve, that they are all ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Hollanders,</hi> true Proteſtants, and Perſons of deep foreſight, and for the moſt part, Men of Learning. That is to ſay, they are Men who have frequently expos'd their Lives for their Religion and the Liberty of their Country. Add to this that the Souls of Learned Men are too highly exalted above the mean thoughts of Treaſon and Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and their Hearts too generous to be capable of Baſeneſs and Perfidy; nor will the Spirit of Popery and Tyranny ever accord with Philoſophic Liberty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41191:20"/>There is this alſo farther to be ſaid that though a Prince and his Counſel ſhould have vow'd their own ruin, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring againſt the Repoſe and Priviledges of two Nations, it would be impoſſible for them to accompliſh their deſign. 'I is true that if a Nation accuſtom'd to <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> and Slavery, happens to ſubdue a free People, 'tis very probable that the Victors will raviſh from them their ancient Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes if they can do it without looſing the Fruit of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, for that it muſt needs be a trouble to the Victors that the condition of the vanquiſh'd ſhould be better then theirs. Nevertheleſs it does not always ſo happen. For the Courts of <hi>Flanders</hi> and Dukes of <hi>Burgundy</hi> in vain attempted ſeveral times to accuſtom their Subjects of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> Manners. And the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſo ſenſible of their Error in endeavouring to introduce the Inquiſition into thoſe Provinces, that they were forc'd to permit them to enjoy whatever they had remaining of their ancient Priviledges.</p>
               <p>But when two free People are United together, their U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion fortifies their Liberty, againſt all thoſe that would go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to invade it. <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> have often experienc'd the truth of this, tho it can hardly be ſaid that they obey'd the ſame <hi>Line</hi> for a whole Century of Years together.</p>
               <p>Not to inſiſt upon time paſt, 'tis well known that <hi>James</hi> the Second had already adventur'd to declare himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with an Arbitrary Power in reference to the <hi>Scots:</hi> And if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had not call'd in the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to their Aſſiſtance, their late King would not have ſtopt there. By which it is clearly to be ſeen, that there is ſo little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to be Jealous of their new Governour, or for the People of <hi>Great Britain</hi> to repent their having ſet the Crown upon the Head of a Prince ſo powerful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that on the contrary the Puiſſance of their Supreme Chieſtain is their proper and ſafeſt ſecurity; ſince it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Will nor in his Power to make uſe of it to their Hurt; and for that their Security under him will protect
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41191:20"/>
them from all the Aſſaults of <hi>France,</hi> which taking Advantage of their Diviſions, advanc'd within a little of ruining both the one and the other.</p>
               <p>The three other Objections are ſo inconſiderable that they are not worth the trouble of inſiſting upon them. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs we ſhall refute them in a few words, leaſt ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Reader ſhould believe we avoid the medling with them. The Prince is a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> by Birth, therefore he will favour the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and leſſen the Authority of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> 'Tis a ſtrange thing that the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> who hardly know their own Religion, ſhould pretend to teach us ours.</p>
               <p>They have been told a thouſand times that the Biſhops and Presbyterians of <hi>England</hi> differ only in ſo ſlight Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which are nothing to the Eſſential part of Divine Worſhip, and that there is more of Obſtinacy and Miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding between them, then of real Cauſe of Diſpute. We have ſeen at the <hi>Hugue</hi> for this ten or twelve Years, the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> now Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> repair in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently ſometimes to the <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>French</hi> Church, and ſometimes to her own Chappel. The Prince no ſooner ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at <hi>London,</hi> but he receiv'd the Communion in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Church, and gave a favourable Reception to the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters who went to Congratulate him. We ſee every day ſeveral of the Epiſcopal Party Communicate with the Reformed on this ſide the Sea, and our <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> Proteſtants joyn themſelves with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Yet, maugre all this, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctors would make us believe we are of two Religions. And upon the ſame ſcore becauſe their Religion properly conſiſts only in exterior Pomp, in Images, Relics, Beds, Roſaries, Holy-water, Monks of ſeveral Colours, and ſuch like Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Exerciſes and Inſtitutions; and that thoſe other things wherein they differ from the Proteſtants are only the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of <hi>Italian</hi> Policy, they imagin it to be the ſame with ours. Whence it comes to paſs that all the Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41191:21"/>
Opinions of our Divines are by thoſe Gentlemen lookt upon as ſo many. All the Confeſſions of Faith, the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, the Ceremonies in the Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Varieties of Diſcipline, the Orders and Habits of the Preachers, if our Adverſaries were ſo to be believ'd, among us make ſo many different Sects. For this reaſon it was that a certain Prelate, who believ'd himſelf to be very witty, has made a Hiſtory of the Variations of our Churches, and he had ſo great a deſire to augment the Number that he bethought himſelf of aſcribing to us as many Relics as he found Syſtems of our Miniſters upon the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> the moſt obſcure Book of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs we muſt acknowledge that the Headſtrong Obſtinacy of ſome of Ours, and the remains of Ignorance and the Spirit of <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> that will not yet out of the Bones of ſome that Envy our Unity, have given oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to theſe Calumnies. The <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church has mourn'd for above theſe ten Centuries, under the Darkneſs and Yoke of Popery. During which time there was Opportunity and Advantage enough to deepen the Superſtitions, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Popery under ſo wicked a Maſter. Add to this, that ſince the Reformation, we have not had a Prince whoſe Knowledg, Piety and Puiſſance have been able to reconcile our Differences. The Great <hi>Guſtavus</hi> had conceiv'd ſuch a Deſign in his Mind, but he vaniſh'd like a flaſh of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the midſt of his Victories. It ſeems that God has reſerv'd this Honour for <hi>William</hi> the III. and this Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs till our Time. God has ſent this Prince into the World in a Country, where the Spirit of Toleration has paſs'd from the Magiſtrates to the moſt Learned Miniſters. He has call'd him to a Kingdom repleniſh'd with Learned and Pious Biſhops, who have for a long time preſerv'd their Flocks in Peace by their gentleneſs and moderation. The Prince at hi firſt Coming to the Government found Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Church, as well as in the State. He has appeas'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41191:21"/>
both the one and the other. The Perſecution of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in <hi>France,</hi> has open'd, the Eyes of all their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and has ſhew'd them the neceſſity of guarding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Fury of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> All theſe Conjunctures in my Opinion preſage a happy Union of the Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>As to what is ſaid, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> then any of his Predeceſſors, is an Equivocation. For ever ſince the Eſtabliſhment of the Commonwealth, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have always born a very great Affection to the Houſe of <hi>Orange:</hi> but true it is that ever ſince <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Silent,</hi> who laid the firſt Foundations of their Liberty, this State never had a Prince whom they lov'd more then <hi>William Henry.</hi> The reaſon is becauſe he enter'd upon the Government at a time, when the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſeem'd to be ruin'd beyond recovery; and yet he reſtor'd them to their former Grandeur.</p>
               <p>However, notwithſtanding this ſignal Service done them, the dread of War and certain vain Suſpitions were the Cauſe that there was great Oppoſition made againſt a <hi>Levie</hi> of ſixteen Thouſand Men, which the Prince moſt earneſtly preſs'd for, as better underſtanding the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> then any of the <hi>Burgomaſters</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> The Event de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated that never was any Oppoſition made upon ſuch bad Grounds, nor more Prejudicial to the State. For <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. boaſted in the Edict which revokes that of <hi>Nantes</hi> that he had not made the Truce but to Exterminate the Proteſtants out of his Kingdom. <hi>James</hi> the II. took that time to perplex the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to invade the Liberties of his People. At length <hi>France</hi> threw off her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mask, and broke the Truce, as ſoon as ſhe thought ſhe could do it with Advantage. That long Train of Deluſions juſtify'd the Prince's Innocence; ſhew'd that he had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Aim in all his Deſigns, but the Preſervation of Liberty and the Proteſtant Religion, and gain'd him the Hearts of all the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> And I would fain know how long it has
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41191:22"/>
been a Crime for a Governour to win the Love of thoſe who are under his Conduct?</p>
               <p>Thus you may ſee how the firſt Prince <hi>William</hi> render'd himſelf Abſolute; and how the ſame Power came to be transferr'd to his Succeſſors; not by Uſurpation, but by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Liberty of the <hi>Republic.</hi> The form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſtill the ſame, the Elections are made by the uſual Suffrages; the Reſolutions taken for the raiſing of Money, making Peace and War, Affairs of Trade. Juſtice and Civil Government, are all determin'd in the Aſſembly of Eſtates according to the Ancient Cuſtoms: and we are ready to make it appear that for theſe fifteen Years laſt paſt, that <hi>William Henry</hi> has ſate at the Helm, he has acted nothing but according to the Laws, and by vertue of the power an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd to his high Authority and Command.</p>
               <p>As to what is reported, that the Prince engag'd the <hi>States General</hi> in his Expedition for <hi>England,</hi> without imparting to them his Deſign, is a Calumny of his Enemies, which has no other foundation but the Malice of thoſe who are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd that he did not make a diſcovery of that Fortunate Enterprize at ſuch a time, that they might have had more leiſure to prepare to obſtruct him. And it is an eaſie thing to convince all Intelligent Perſons of the Folly of this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe this Revolution had been the Effect of long deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration; it was neceſſary, before all other things, 1. To be aſſur'd of the Inclinations of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> and the Collonies depending upon Them. In theſe Tranſactions, the Prince not acting as Governour of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> but as a Private perſon managing his own proper Affairs, he was not oblig'd to make his buſineſs known to the <hi>States General.</hi> Nevertheleſs, I make no queſtion but the Principal Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peices among them were well inform'd from the beginning of the Deſign; which is a thing indeed not to be doubted, conſidering the good Intelligence there has been at the <hi>Hague</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41191:22"/>
for ſeveral Years laſt paſt; and the unanimous Conſent of their <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mightineſſeſs</hi> when the Queſtion was debated, whether they ſhould lend their helping hand to carry on the Work!</p>
               <p>2. Since the Defeat of the D. of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and the Dragoon Perſecutions, <hi>France</hi> and the Court of <hi>England</hi> never ceas'd to moleſt and diſquiet the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi> They Exaſperated the <hi>Algerines</hi> againſt them, who adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd to exerciſe their Pyracies upon the Coaſt of <hi>Holland. James</hi> the II. ſet open his Ports to thoſe <hi>Corſairs,</hi> and ſuffer'd them publicly to ſell the Prizes which they had taken from his Allies. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. ſought an occaſion to pick a Quarrel with the Subjects of the <hi>States</hi> in the <hi>Streights</hi> of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> forbid the Sale of their Herrings, and their Cloath in his Kingdom, and laid Impoſitions upon all their Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes enter'd in his Ports. In a Word, ſince the Deſign for the repeal of the Teſts, and the Attempts upon Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> there has been nothing but Memoirs, Complaints and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings on both ſides. It was eaſie for the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to ſee, that the Two Princes had conſpir'd their Ruin; ſo that the leaſt they could do was to Arm and ſtand on their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Therefore they rig out a Fleet to protect themſelves from the <hi>Algerines,</hi> and the Threats of <hi>France.</hi> Thereupon out comes the Letter of the Deceas'd Monſieur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Fagel,</hi> that the Court of <hi>England</hi> was drawn into a Conjunction with <hi>France</hi> by the force of Intreaties, Promiſes and Menaces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated one upon the Neck of another. The Miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding increaſes, and King <hi>James</hi> keeps an Army on Foot contrary to the Laws of the Land, the Queen is feign'd to be with Child, and a Counterfeit Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon the Nation. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> reinforce their Army and Navy both by Sea and Land: The <hi>French</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double their Threats and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> their Murmurs. The latter at length preſent a Memorial to their Royal Highneſſes, wherein they ſet forth the Cauſe of their Complaints, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41191:23"/>
invite the Prince to come over and procure the Calling of a Parliament. The Prince condeſcends to their earneſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, the <hi>States</hi> Conſent, Aſſiſt him with Ships and Souldiers to prevent any Attempt upon his Perſon? The Prince puts to Sea, accompany'd with the Bleſſing of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the Acclamations of the People, and he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerv'd into <hi>England</hi> with the ſame Joy, as was ſeen at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of <hi>Holland.</hi> This was that which was both ſeen and known to all the Land. What can be from hence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, but that there was a great deal of Patience and Prudence on the one ſide, and Violence and Raſhneſs on the other? So that all that the View of this Tranſaction could encline a rational Perſon to was only this, to have a Compaſſion for <hi>James</hi> the II. and a High Eſteem for his Competitor.</p>
               <p>But it behoves us to be Candid and to acknowledge, that the Fortunate Aſſemblage of all theſe Circumſtances would not perhaps have been ſufficient, had they been only favour'd by Perſons of leſs exalted Degree, then their Royal Highneſſes were. They are both of them Proteſtants not only by Birth and Education, but alſo through Affection and choice of a more Underſtanding; they are of eaſie Acceſs and Affable, their Converſation Civil and Vertuous; they keep their words exactly; they make it their glory to leave nothing imperfect but to accompliſh whatever they take in hand, not enduring the repulſe of whatſoever dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers they ſee before them. They never Abandon thoſe that ſerve them faithfully, but reward them liberally: they are neither ſway'd by Humour our nor difficult to Content, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forgive Offences not maliciouſly committed. They are endow'd with Wiſdom, Piety and Vertue; Great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouragers of Learning and Learned Men, and particularly Church-men. Such Qualities as theſe would recommend a Private Perſon to the higheſt Dignities; but where they meet in Perſons of Royal Extraction, what wonder if they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41191:23"/>
win upon the Affections of the People. The Valour and Vigilance of the Prince, his Experience in Military Diſcipline, and his inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable Fervency in <hi>Combat</hi> gain him the Hearts of his Souldiers and Allies, his Prudence and peircing Judgment, cauſe him to be eſteem'd by Men of the ſublimeſt intellects; and his probity and ſincerity command the Reverence of good Men. His Reputation is ſo uncontroulable, that the Court of <hi>England,</hi> could never lay any other thing to his Charge but the rigorous Severity of his Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Diſcipline. The Love which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have for him is ſo general, that among the vaſt Number of Writers wiſh which that <hi>State</hi> is crowded, of which ſo many take the Liberty to ſpeak their Minds with freedom enough, there never was but one that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to Calumniate the Princes Expedition into <hi>England;</hi> but the Book had ſo few Readers and ſold ſo ill, thatit preſently became waſt Paper. Theſe were the Reaſons of the great Succeſs of <hi>Willtam</hi> the III. For in regard that all the World had a great Love for him, in regard his Deſigns were equally Juſt, Pious and Beneficial, that he went to ſecure his Country, to deliver his Oppreſs'd Brethern and Neighbours, and to Re-eſtabliſh the Proteſtant Religion and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Nation, every body glory'd in contributing to it; no body betray'd him, tho he had ſeveral Confidents; and the <hi>States</hi> lent him their Helping hand ſo ſoon as all things were ready. And this was that which made ſeveral Strangers believe, that this Deſign, till it was ripe for Execution, lay depoſited in the Breaſts of certain faithful Counſellors, who then by a more then uſual Dexterity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd their <hi>High and Mightineſſes</hi> in the Affair. But the truth is, that ſeveral Perſons were acquainted with it, and that they were ſway'd rather by Love then Policy. The Secrecy with which the King of <hi>France</hi> manages his Affairs is greatly wonder'd at; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is a thing much to be commended, but it is very rare. Tho for ten or twelve Counſellors whoſe Fortune wholly depends upon the King, to be faithful to him and keep his Secrets is no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary peice of buſineſs. But for an infinite Number of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters, of Lords, Magiſtrates and Private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to keep ſilence ſo long and to be ſo true one to another, is that which hardly ever yet was known.</p>
               <p>And therefore the beſt Counſel that can be given to our Enemies would be ſpeedily to make a Peace with a Prince ſo well belov'd by his own Subjects, and ſo formidable to his Adverſaries: For the time will come, that he will deſpiſe their Offers. They vainly flatter
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41191:24"/>
themſelves to ſeduce the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> during the Kings abode in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or to raiſe Diſturbances in <hi>England,</hi> while he remains in <hi>Holland.</hi> 'Tis true that feeble Affection which is ſupported only by Fancy, or only grounded upon ſome Conformity of Temper and Humour is as frail, as the Foundation is ſlight: But when Religion, Vertue and the public Intereſt are the Bonds of Union between the Prince and Subjects, it is a Link inſeparable, which the abſence of ſome few Months renders much the ſtronger. Now the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the two Nations bear to his moſt Serene Majeſty <hi>William</hi> the III. is of the latter ſort. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> are a Warlike Nation that paſſionately Loves their Kings, eſpecially when their Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are Martial. Their Princes have for a long time enjoy'd both <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Guyenne,</hi> which oblig'd them frequently to croſs the Sea; but we never read in any Hiſtory that their Subjects took any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their abſence to riſe up in Rebellion. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> ever ſince their firſt Confederacy having been almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually engag'd in Wars, are more accuſtom'd to ſee their Prince at the Head of their Armies, then at leiſure at the <hi>Hague.</hi> So that both the one and the other will eaſily be contented that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhould viſit them by turns. Beſides that, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will have Queen <hi>Mary</hi> always preſent in their Capital City, whoſe Piety and Vertue, whoſe great Underſtanding and Mildneſs renders her equal to <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> a Perſon to whom the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were ſo devoted, that at her departure the chiefeſt of their wiſhes were that ſhe might be but as well belov'd at <hi>London,</hi> as ſhe had been at the <hi>Hague;</hi> to which her Royal Highneſs anſwer'd, that ſhe deſir'd no more.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the greateſt Difficulties that are propounded and buzz'd abroad by our Male Contents, or which I have been able to think of. Their weakneſs appears to me a certain preſage of the felicity of the People under the Reign of <hi>William</hi> the III. and <hi>Mary</hi> the II. and of that Peace which the Union between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> will reſtore to <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41191:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The SECOND PART.</hi> The Happy Conſequences of the <hi>Union</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>FRANCE</hi> and <hi>HOLLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The Means to preſerve it entire.</head>
               <p>AMong the happy Conſequences of the Union between the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their Majeſties of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of their <hi>High and Mightineſſes,</hi> there are ſome which are particular to each of the two Nations; and relate to the form of Government, their Laws and Priviledges. But it belongs not to a private Perſon to meddle with thoſe ſorts of Matters, as being the buſineſs of Parliaments and Aſſemblies of Eſtates. Other Conſequences there are more general, wherein divers Confederate Princes, ſeveral Countries, all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and all <hi>Europe</hi> find themſelves intereſted, and upon which we ſhall make ſome Reflections.</p>
               <p>I place in the firſt ranck, the bringing down the Power of <hi>France;</hi> not believing that I could begin with a more pleaſing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Since the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace that Kingdom has mounted to a Degree of Grandeur and Pride which have render'd <hi>France</hi> inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable to all her Neighbours; ſo that it is neither the Wealth nor the Welfare of the <hi>French</hi> People that are envy'd (for Men have more reaſon to be mov'd with Compaſſion at the ſight of their Miſeries.) 'Tis againſt their blindneſs that Men exclaim, and that indiſpenſable fury that hurries them on to make others as miſerable as themſelves; inſtead of complying with their good Intentions, and permitting the releaſe of thoſe miſerable People from the ſad Condition wherein they are. If <hi>France</hi> were enrich'd by Trade, by Manufacture, by a long Peace; if it were aggrandiz'd by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages and Alliances, by the free Conceſſions of Princes, or by the vaſt Concurrences and Conflux of People to her Territories, we ſhould be ſo far from troubling her repoſe, that we ſhould do our utmoſt to imitate her Example. But it is well known that her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and her Riches are the Effects of Breach of Faith, and her
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41191:25"/>
unjuſt Wars, of her Vexations and Oppreſſions, and the vaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions which ſhe exacts from the People; ſo that the generality of the Subjects are reduc'd by the Court to that Condition as not to be able to ſubſiſt but in the midſt of the Rage of War, by Pillage, Robbery and Ranſack.</p>
               <p>The bare Duties of Humanity would oblige their Neighbours to redeem them from a Condition ſo oppoſite to the public good and the Salvation of their Souls; nor is the particular Intereſt of other People an Obligation leſs engaging to the ſame Effect. Since that under the pretence of Religion, the Dragoons have ruin'd the beſt Families in the Kingdom, waſted their Eſtates, and diſabl'd the Proprietors to make the beſt of their demeans, and to continue their Trades: ſince as an Accumulation of their Misfortune, the Privateers being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Maſters of the Seas, Trade has undergon ſo ſenſible a decay, that ten Years more, like the three laſt, will produce a far greater miſchief then a general Peſtilence for ten Months; in regard they would be the ruin of an infinite Number of Families, which by means of their Wealth and Induſtry, are at preſent the ſupport and glory of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſidering the preſent Conſtitution of our Weſtern Parts, the Wines, the Strong-waters, the Oyl and Salt of <hi>France,</hi> are Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes which Foreigners can hardly live without. But the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants being impoveriſh'd, and not able to burthen themſelves with thoſe things which would be given them in exchange, they that want their Wares, muſt be oblig'd to carry ready Money, and to afford new Matter to feed the Extortions of the Collectors, and the Inſatiable Avarice of the <hi>Chief Miniſters.</hi> Add to this, that if the War happen to ſpin out in length, the great Number of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that muſt be rais'd throughout the Kingdom, will be the cauſe that the greateſt part of the Lands muſt lye untill'd; and that the infinite Wealth accrewing by the profits of the Land would be all loſt.</p>
               <p>If it be ſo then, ſome will ſay, that it is ſo much the Intereſt of Foreigners to Labour the preſervation of <hi>France,</hi> it behoves them ſpeedily to make a Peace with her. 'Tis very true, that there could be nothing more advantageous then a general Peace; but the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that conſidering the preſent Condition of Affairs, it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſafe nor poſſible to conclude a Peace; beſides that, it is alſo more uncertain and more difficult to be aſſur'd that it ſhall be of any long continuance. Therefore before we talk of Peace, it will be requiſite. 1. That <hi>Lemis</hi> the XIV. Re-eſtabliſh the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41191:25"/>
the <hi>Reformed</hi> to the ſame Condition wherein they were before the Death of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. and make reſtitution of all the Damages which they have ſuſtain'd ſince the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Peace; but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince the Truce in the Year—84. It would be an eternal Ignominy to the Proteſtants, to ſuffer the public Violation of the Treaties concluded with their Brethren, without alledging any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, but only that they are not <hi>Roman Catholics,</hi> nor of the King's Religion. If theſe Reaſons could take Place, or that a Prince could break his Promiſes made to his Subjects and perſecute them with Fire and Sword, meerly becauſe they are not Chriſtians after his manner, what ſhall hinder him from breaking the Contracts made with his Allies, that are of another belief which is different from his?</p>
               <p>2. If the public Faith engages the Proteſtants States to reſtore the <hi>Reformed</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> it alſo excites the Catholic Potentates to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Satisfaction for the Injuries done them by that Crown, which has omitted no ſort of Uſurpations, increaſe to it's Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur either by unjuſt Wars, or in full Peace. Therefore it is but requiſite, that now for the obtaining of Peace, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. ſhould make reparation for all his Neighbours loſſes, of which himſelf has been the occaſion in the laſt War, ſince the Treaty of <hi>Nimeghen</hi> and the Breach of the Truce; that he reſtore what he unjuſtly detains from the <hi>Empire,</hi> from <hi>Spain,</hi> from the King of <hi>England,</hi> from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> from the <hi>Electors,</hi> the D. of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. The King of <hi>France</hi> never failing of Pretences to break the moſt Sacred Leagues, no body that I know would be willing to truſt him, nor to be <hi>Guarantees</hi> for the performance of the offers he ſhould make, unleſs it were the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> with whom he has renew'd and confirm'd his Ancient Alliances. And therefore it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that he ſurrender up ſeveral ſtrong Towns and Garriſons as Pledges for his performance, upon condition that they ſhall remain confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcated to the Parties into whoſe hands they are ſurrender'd, in caſe he break the Peace to be concluded.</p>
               <p>Now in regard it is moſt certain that <hi>France</hi> will find ſuch Articles very burthenſome, at leaſt that ſhe will never ſubſcribe or put them in Execution, there is no Foundation to be laid upon her promiſes; whence it is clear, that to procure the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that ſhe muſt be conſtrain'd to it by Attacquing her on ſeveral ſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:41191:26"/>This will be no difficult thing to bring to paſs, if the <hi>Empire, Spain, England, Swedeland</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> confirm their Alliance, and if the Confederates create a particular General, to the end that their Forces United under one <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> may act by conſent and unanimouſlyagainſt the common Enemy.</p>
               <p>In all times, miſunderſtanding has ruin'd the ſtrongeſt Leagues; of which we have ſeen frequent and fatal Examples in the laſt War. If <hi>France</hi> therefore can yet find any means to diſunite the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, they may aſſure themſelves that the opportunity for pulling down the Power of <hi>France</hi> will not be long in their hands. <hi>France</hi> will make uſe of her uſual methods, by bribing the Governors of Garriſons, corrupting the Treaſurer's, that the Army may ſtil want either Money or Proviſion; by gaining the cheif Miniſters of the ſeveral Courts, on purpoſe to make falſe reports to their Maſters, or impertinent and unſeaſonable Orders to the Generals, and ſowing jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſies between them, to make them draw off one from another in the greateſt urgency of Affairs. And it is very probable that the greateſt part of theſe misfortunes will not fail to happen, if the Confederates do not agree to confer the ſupream command of General upon one Perſon, in whoſe power it ſhall be to make the whole Body Act Unanimouſly, and who ſhall have Reputation and Authority ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to reſtrain the inferior Generals within the bounds of their duty.</p>
               <p>We are verily perſwaded, that neither Flatteries, Promiſes, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, no <hi>Lewis</hi>'s of Gold, will be able to diſarm the Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Therefore <hi>France</hi> begins to deſpair of ſeducing them that way, but gives it out that this is a War for the ſake of Religion; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that the Catholic Potentates ought to unite with her to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Eſtabliſhing the Reformation all over <hi>Europe.</hi> But it is the ruin of his <hi>Matchiavillian</hi> Politics which he dreads more then the Eſtabliſhment of the Reformation. In the mean while the pretence is ſpecious, becauſe he judges of others by himſelf, and for that the Zeal of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy puſhing him on to deſtroy the pretended <hi>Heretics,</hi> he imagins the Reſolutions of the reformed to be the ſame.</p>
               <p>This is an Error of which it is of great Importance to convince theſe Gentlemen; though it be no difficult thing to undeceive them, if they will but take the pains to mind the following Reflections.</p>
               <p>1. That it is a Fundamental maxim of the Reformation, that every Man has a right to examin the Religion he intends to profeſs;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41191:26"/>
to judge of it by his own underſtanding, and to believe nothing but what he is perſwaded of the Truth in his Conſcience. Whence the Proteſtants infer, that no human Authority ought to force Men to exerciſe a Worſhip which they believe unlawful, or to profeſs an Opinion which they concieve to be falſe.</p>
               <p>Clear it is, that this Doctrin is directly oppoſite to the Spirit of Perſecution; for if it be not lawful for the Paſtors to conſtrain Chriſtians to believe or practiſe what they hold to be falſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God; much leſs is it lawful to employ the Power of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Arm to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies nothing to ſay, that among us we Excommunicate <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics,</hi> or that we have frequently Perſecuted Miniſters and Private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the ſame reaſon. For as for Excommunication, in reſpect of Speculative Opinions it is no more of it's ſelf then a bare Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſuch or ſuch a one, has not thoſe Qualities which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to fit him to be a Member of ſuch or ſuch a Society. In which caſe, it is not accompany'd with any mark of Infamy or civil Puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe for Example that any Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is perſwaded, that Epiſcopacy is no lawful Government, that he cannot in conſcience preach upon Holy-days, or perform other Functions to which the Miniſtry obliges him; and that thereupon he goes to his <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> and lays down his Function; promiſing all the reſt of his life to live quietly at home, or in Communion with the Faithful; Sure I am that if they could not undeceive him, they would bewayl his Ignorance; but yet they would be ſo far from uſing him as a Criminal, that they would admire his Probity. But if the ſame Divine ſhould make uſe of the Liberty of his Function to excite the People to contemn the Biſhops, and to trample their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions under foot, by ſhewing them himſelf an ill example; then it would be but juſt to puniſh him, not as a Perſon that holds errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinions, but as a diſturber of the Public Peace.</p>
               <p>This Maxim takes no farther place then to preſerve the order and unity of Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline; for Politic Toleration is ſo much in practiſe among the Proteſtants, that as well the particular Members of their Body, as thoſe that are not of the Communion of their Churches, have all the liberty to believe and ſay what they think fitting in reſpect of Religion, provided they do not broach Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties or trouble the State with Factions and Cabals.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:41191:27"/>2. The Spirit of Infallibility is ſo natural to Men that are Proud and full of ſelf Love, and is ſo linkt with the deſire of advancing their own ſentiments, that we have no cauſe to wonder that the Reformed have retain'd ſome ſmall remainder of this Leven; as being ſprung from a Church which holds Infallibility for one of its Fundamental Doctrins, and conveighs it from the Head to all its Members. But during the laſt Perſecution, the Proteſtants have written ſo many Treatiſes to deſtroy that wicked Principle; they have teſtify'd ſuch an Abhorrency of all manner of Perſecution both in their private and public diſcourſes; they have demonſtrated in ſuch a convincing manner that truth perſwades, but never forces; that God alone is the ſole Lord of the Heart, and that to attempt to force it, would be an Attack upon the Prerogative of the ſupream Majeſty, that though Conſcience and the Spirit of Religion ſhould not encline them to ſupport all others their fellow Chriſtians, the Honour of obſerving one equal conduct, and the ſhame of contradicting themſelves, would perſwade them to Toleration.</p>
               <p>3. Before we believe that Intelligent Perſons are capable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thoſe faults which they deteſt, and which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Principles, we ought to examin whether there be any conceal'd motive of Intereſt which inclines them to ſuch abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditys. Thus though Pope <hi>Pelagius,</hi> the fourth <hi>Lateran Council,</hi> and ſeveral other Pontiffs and Aſſemblies of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> had not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniz'd the Perſecution of the <hi>Heretics,</hi> though the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtance</hi> had never declar'd it to be lawful to break faith with the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> though the ſame Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had never put theſe Principles in Practice by Impriſonment, Exile, Proſcription, and torments of ſuch Chriſtians as were not within the pale of their Communion, yet we had reaſon to ſuſpect her guilty of this deſign, becauſe it is perfectly agreeable to their Intereſts. The <hi>Roman Clergy</hi> is a Monarchical Body, of which all the ſeveral Members are in a capacity of Aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, not only to the higheſt employments both in Church and State, but even to Soveraignty it ſelf. Now the more numerous theſe dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and employments are, the more reaſon have Private Perſons to hope; and as certain it is that extent of Empire encreaſes the Number of Preferments. Therefore it is, that in all Monarchies that incline to Tyranny, the ſureſt means to extend their dominion, is to carry as high as may be the Soveraign Prerogative, though at the expence of the Peoples liberty. Then again, beſides the ſecular Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtics, there are infinite ſwarms of <hi>Monks</hi> whoſe principal
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41191:27"/>
buſineſs it is to extend the bounds of the Pontifical Empire; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the vaſter it is, the richer, the more powerful, and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected their ſeveral Societies will be; and the more the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Particular Perſons. Now the <hi>Reformed</hi> are the declar'd Enemies of this Church; they not only refuſe Obedience to the Head of it, to acknowledge it's Miniſters and Officers, or to admit of it's Maxims; but they alſo ruin the Foundations of its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, in Preaching down the <hi>Maſs,</hi> Indulgencies, Purgatory they drain and dry up the very Fountains of its Wealth by contemning Images, Relics, Invocation of Saints, Bulls and Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations from <hi>Rome,</hi> they deſtroy the reſpect and reverence which the People have for it, in rejecting it's Infallibility, Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Adoration of Saints, and the refuſal of the Cup to the Laity. Who can doubt after all this, but that the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Monks</hi> and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>Rome</hi> are mainly intereſted to extinguiſh the Reformation, and extirpate the Reformed?</p>
               <p>It is not ſo with the Proteſtants; in regard that neither their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, nor their Intereſt prompt them to Perſecute the <hi>Catholics.</hi> I muſt acknowledge, that tis for the glory and reputation of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Biſhops, that all the Subjects of the Kingdom ſhould be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> But neither their Jurisdiction nor their Revenues would be much enlarged by the conjunction of the <hi>Roman Catholics.</hi> As for the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> in other States, all the profit which they get by the converſion of their Adverſaries, is to have a more numerous Auditory in ſome places, and to be at more trouble in viſiting their Pariſhioners.</p>
               <p>4. But what neceſſity of Phyſical Reffections where the thing ſpeaks it ſelf? You ſhall never find our Biſhops, nor our Miniſters rambling over Sea and Land, and Vagabonding about the World to gain <hi>Proſelites,</hi> nor Beſieging the Houſes of the public Magiſtrates to obtain decrees againſt the <hi>Roman Catholics.</hi> Our Princes and our Governors ſuffer them to live unmoleſted, at the ſame time that they Perſecute our Brethren. In a word the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are all a ſort of Republicans, whoſe Government is <hi>Ariſtocratical</hi> in <hi>England, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratical</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and compoſed of both among the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> but no where Monarchical: So that all they mind is to preſerve themſelves in Peace without giving any trouble to others. Thus the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> have no cauſe to miſtruſt us, and it is long of them, that we do not live together like Brethren, at leaſt like Chriſtians and good Friends. Therefore let them ſurceaſe to hate and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute us, for we wiſh them no ill, and we likewiſe offer to bury in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41191:28"/>
Oblivion all the miſcheifs they have caus'd us to ſuffer, in favour of thoſe who ſhall joyn themſelves with us to extirpate Tyranny, and reeſtabliſh the <hi>PEACE OF E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> that Soveraign Good, the Perfection and Fountain of all the Reſt, which will naturally ſpring from the debaſing and humbling the Power of <hi>France:</hi> and this is that, which they who underſtand the deſigns and Pretenſions of that Crown, will eaſily apprehend by giving never ſo little Attention to what we are going to ſay.</p>
               <p>The Grand complaint againſt that Monarchy is for pretending to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy;</hi> Nor are they miſtaken in their Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And I dare affirm, that had it not been for the great Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>France</hi> was upon the Point of obtaining what ſhe had been ſo thirſting after. People will ſay perhaps, that ſhe had ſeveral Countries yet to conquer. But I could anſwer that all the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> was not in a condition to make much reſiſtance. The <hi>Emperor</hi> and the <hi>Venetians</hi> engag'd in a War againſt the <hi>Turk, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> ally'd to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. <hi>Spain</hi> exhauſted and under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a Woman, [<hi>dead ſome weeks ago</hi>] that had a kindneſs for her own Country, <hi>Portugal</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> almoſt in the ſame condition; the King of <hi>England</hi> embroyl'd and in confuſion at home, and <hi>Germany</hi> divided. What could <hi>Sweden</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> have done. They would only have been glad to have been the laſt attacqu'd.</p>
               <p>But it may be reply'd, that we live not in thoſe conquering times, nor in thoſe Ages when they were wont to bring all into the Feild that were able to bear Arms, or when two or three Battels decided the Deſtiny of <hi>Empires;</hi> that according to the manner of ſpinning out a War now a days the lives of five or ſix Kings equally Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous would not ſuffice to Conquer all <hi>Europe.</hi> To which I have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwer to make; that the ſame methods are not taken, nor the ſame ways us'd as formerly to gain the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy.</hi> The People of <hi>Europe</hi> are ſo accuſtom'd to be rul'd by different Princes, that there would be little reaſon to fear a King who ſhould conceive a deſign to ſubdue them all, and afterwards to govern them by his Lieutenants; in regard his deſign would be no leſs fantaſtic then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. A <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch</hi> then, at preſent, is quite another thing then an Abſolute Prince at home, and who has reduc'd his Neighbours ſo low that they are not able to enterprize any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; that they are conſtrain'd to brook his outrages and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and to ſuffer him to do what he pleaſes. Now is there any
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41191:28"/>
Perſon of good credit that can deny but that <hi>France</hi> was almoſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at this high Pitch of Grandeur and that in all outward Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he had attain'd to what he deſir'd, had <hi>James</hi> 11. his faithful Ally, kept firm upon his Throne.</p>
               <p>Now let the Confederates conſider whether it be not their intereſt to humble the Pride of <hi>France,</hi> and whether they will ever meet with an opportunity more Favourable. Not that I would adviſe them to the Tryal of an Abſolute conqueſt of <hi>France;</hi> but if they can but regain what ſhe has wreſted from them, reſtore the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> to his own, and as occaſion offers, ſever the Dukedoms of <hi>Normandy, Britain</hi> and <hi>Guyen</hi> as formerly they were divided, and which is no more then what is long'd for by the inhabitants at this day; take advantage of the diſcontents of the People to re-eſtabliſh the cuſtom of calling free <hi>Aſſemblies of Eſtates,</hi> and in a Word divide that vaſt Kingdom into ſeveral Principalities, and reduce it to the ſame condition wherein it was toward the end of the Second Race, and at the beginning of the Third, before <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt;</hi> at what time the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> had ſomething elſe to do then trouble their Brains about diſturbing their Neighbours quiet.</p>
               <p>Perhaps ſome <hi>French man</hi> will tell me I am a Traytor to my Nation, and give that Advice which is enough to embroyl the Kingdom in Civil War. But there is nothing of that in my deſign; for I dare proteſt with a ſafe conſcience that my Principal aim is only to aſuſt my fellow Country-men in the recovery of their liberty. Though if they cannot recover it but by a Civil War, that may laſt for ſome Years, is it not infinitely to be prefer'd before an eternal ſlavery? But ſay my oppoſers, theſe Petty Princes will be always quarrelling one with another? And do not the great ones do the ſame? Let the Counts of <hi>Foix</hi> and <hi>Armagnac</hi> fight it out as long as they pleaſe, the reſt of <hi>France</hi> takes no notice of their brawls. But when <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. Rendevouzes three hundred thouſand Men, he drains and depopulates a great Kingdom, and ſtrikes ſuch a terror into all his Neighbours, that they are compell'd to oppreſs their People, to withſtand his Invaſions, beſides a War between two petty Princes can never laſt long; for that in a ſhort time they find themſelves both ſo enfeebl'd that they are conſtrain'd to agree. This is the only means to procure a general Peace, and to prevent <hi>France</hi> from breaking the Treaties that ſhall be concluded with her.</p>
               <p>THE REESTABLISHMENT OF THE PRINCES DISPOS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SESS'D, AND OF THE PROTESTANTS EXIL'D is another
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41191:29"/>
of the moſt happy and important conſequences of the Union of the Confederates. Wars are the <hi>Law-ſuits</hi> of Princes, Battels and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts are their Judges; and the miſcheif is that theſe Judges are both blind and inconſtant; and there is always Appeal from their decrees ſo ſoon as the vanquiſh'd finds himſelf in a condition to come to a new Tryal. And therefore that Chriſtendom may be reſtor'd to a general and laſting Peace there is a neceſſity of fixing, as far as lies in mortal Power, the Fate and deſtiny of Armed Deciſions, by bringing the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> to ſuch an equal Ballance, that no one may be eaſily able to oppreſs the Reſt. We have ſought in vain for this Medium, ever ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty; for that the ſtrength of <hi>Spain</hi> decay'd of a ſuddain, and <hi>England</hi> which was only able to oppoſe the Progreſs of the <hi>French,</hi> intended nothing leſs. Now the medal begins to turn; <hi>Great Britain</hi> is at liberty, <hi>Germany</hi> is United, the <hi>Empire</hi> grows powerful; and it may be ſaid without any injury to the valour of the reſt of the Generals, neither to his Highneſs the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> that the <hi>Emperour</hi> is cheifly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for the Victories which he has gain'd over the Grand Enemy of the <hi>Chriſtian Name,</hi> ſince the Seige of <hi>Vienna,</hi> to Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorain.</hi> It would be therefore a great peice of injuſtice, if that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince ſhould not Reap as well the Fruit of his Labours, as the Honour of having ſo many times triumph'd over the Infidels. <hi>Hangary</hi> being reduc'd, and the Hereditary Countries of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> being ſecured for a long time from the terrour of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Arms, deſerve without doubt, that the <hi>Empire</hi> ſhould do it's utmoſt to reſtore it's Preſerver, to the Inheritance of his Anceſtors. I dare affirm alſo that his Atcheivments are of that importance to the Glory and Repoſe of the Imperial Family, that they ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the memory of this Victorious Champion, and teſtify their acknowledgement to his Poſterity, if Fate prevent them from return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Gratitude to himſelf.</p>
               <p>Intereſt and Vertue are not always Enemies to one another, they agree perfectly well upon this occaſion. The Conqueſts of <hi>France</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> the Invaſion of <hi>Lorain,</hi> of <hi>Franche Conte,</hi> and <hi>Alſatia,</hi> have render'd her ſo potent and ſo near a Neighbour to the <hi>Empire,</hi> that at length in the laſt <hi>Campaign,</hi> ſhe took <hi>Philipſbourgh,</hi> and has almoſt made her ſelf Miſtriſs of the four <hi>Electorats</hi> of the <hi>Rhine.</hi> So that if the revolution in <hi>England,</hi> had not haſten'd her to the defence of her own Country, 'tis very probable that ſhe would have carry'd on her Victories with little or no Obſtruction, Crown'd the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and reduc'd in time the Electors of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41191:29"/>
                  <hi>Saxony, Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the <hi>Landgraves</hi> of <hi>Heſs,</hi> and the reſt of the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> to the ſame condition as the Ancient Dukes of <hi>Normandy, Guyen</hi> and <hi>Burgundy;</hi> that is to ſay, to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> may imagin, that the Re-eſtabliſhment of the Exil'd <hi>Proteſtants</hi> does not concern them; But it more nearly concerns them, then they are aware of. It is ſaid that one of the Cauſes which haſten'd the ruin of the Reformed in <hi>France</hi> was this; becauſe the Court was ſenſible of their diſcontents and murmurings during the War with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi> They were accus'd of holding Intelligence which the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and of diſcovering to them the Secrets of State, and furniſhing them with Money, and ſome of their Miniſters were impriſon'd upon that Account. This was only a Malitious Invention of two or three <hi>Monks;</hi> they never could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Proofs againſt the Parties accus'd, unleſs it were ſome ſlight Expreſſions that dropt unwarily from their Lips; and in regard it was no good Policy to diſcover the weakneſs and diviſions of the Kingdom, the buſineſs was huſht up, and the Perſons let go. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs as it is common for thoſe that are troubled with a bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to fear their own ſhaddows, theſe reports and murmurs made a deep impreſſion in the Minds of the Courtiers. They apprehended that there was nothing ſo dangerous as to ruin People by halves, to provoke a Powerful Body to the higheſt degree and leave them the means to revenge themſelves. Upon which there happen'd a ſlight Inſurrection in <hi>Sevennes</hi> and the <hi>Dauphinate.</hi> Several poor People being gather'd together without any Leader, without any ſupport or defence, a fancy took them to Preach upon the Ruins of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. The Kings Miniſters took the Alarum as if the four Corners of <hi>France</hi> had been on Fire, and being ſecure of <hi>England,</hi> nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending any danger from the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> nor <hi>Germany,</hi> after the twenty Years Truce, and the defeat of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> they began the utter Extirpation of the <hi>Reformed,</hi> after that manner which is known to every Body.</p>
               <p>Beſides the Motives to the Perſecution, recited in the firſt Part of this Treatiſe, there is one which has not yet been mention'd, which perhaps is the chiefeſt. For that <hi>France</hi> having laid the Deſign of Invading the <hi>Empire,</hi> was afraid that while ſhe ſhould be buſied in the Execution of it, the <hi>Reformed</hi> ſhould betake themſelves to their Arms in Defence of their Liberties, and their Languiſhing Religion. Let the Reader judge whether this were a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41191:30"/>
groundleſs Fear or no; However it appear'd that the Court was ſtrook with it, by the way which they took to extinguiſh the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in that Kingdom.</p>
               <p>There were two things Aim'd at, in ſending the Dragoons among thoſe People; the firſt was to ruin the beſt Families becauſe they were able to lend Mony, which is the Sinews of the War; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deſtroy the moſt devout and zealous, as being the ſupport of the Religious Societies. Conſtancy is a vertue very rare; exalted Minds and undaunted Courages but few; but they are the Soul that moves the great Body, and like the Salt which preſerves it from Corruption; ſo that when the Soul expires, or the Salt looſes it's ſtrength, the Societies dye or fall into fainting Fits, which are a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Preſage of their utter Deſtruction. Vulgar Courage, or a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of ſome few days or hours, may cauſe a Man to Contemn Death; but it requires a Conſtancy more then <hi>Heroic,</hi> to ſuffer long contriv'd Torments, inceſſantly renew'd, and which one would think would never have an end. This laſt ſort of Torments it was, the moſt unſupportable of all, which the Court of <hi>France</hi> made uſe of to exerciſe their Cruelty upon the <hi>Reformed.</hi> And indeed that Court has been very Succeſsful; for thoſe People that would have deſpis'd a Flaming Bavin, where they had been ſtifled in a quarter of an hour, wanted reſolution to dye a thouſand times in one day.</p>
               <p>Yet ſeveral Perſons of Quality ſaw themſelves deſpoil'd of their Eſtates, depriv'd of their Employments, and torn from their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; and have endur'd Impriſonment and other Ignominious Uſage, till the Cruelty of their Perſecutors was almoſt tyr'd. Great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Common People have undergon all that the Inſolence and Barbariſm of the Dragoons could invent, the moſt Mercileſs and moſt Outragious; nor have there been wanting of the ſeeble Sex, who have ſignaliz'd their Conſtancy. And many of thoſe whom continu'd Torments had conſtrain'd to ſign Ambiguous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith, repenting ſoon after forſook all, and departed the Kingdom, expoſing themſelves to be Condemn'd to the Galleys to be baniſh'd into <hi>Canada,</hi> and to the moſt exquiſite of Torments which have been inflicted upon ſome. Others have refus'd to go to Maſs, and have endur'd the extremity of Torment with a Conſtancy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the former. A good Number have ſtay'd behind in hopes of a ſpeedy Deliverance: Nevertheleſs a Man would hardly believe how many have periſh'd in the midſt of theſe Meſeries; or elſe that ſtill are forc'd to endure their Miſeries in Exile.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:41191:30"/>It cannot be deny'd but that <hi>France</hi> gave it ſelf a very great Wound; Nor did the Court without doubt believe, that the perſwaſion of the truth had ſo much force upon the Souls of Men, becauſe they had never put it to the Tryal. So that finding that the Number of the faint and daſtardly was not ſo great as they thought, they let go thoſe whoſe Conſtancy fortify'd the weak, and ſet open the Gates of the Kingdom for ſome few days, on purpoſe to give the more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous an Opportunity to eſcape, tho they would not ſuffer them to carry any thing along with them.</p>
               <p>It is evident that thoſe of our Brethren who eſcap'd are the moſt Couragious and the moſt Politic, as well as Fortunate. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuppos'd, if the Confederates neglect to reſtore the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> one of theſe two things will neceſſarily follow. the firſt is that the Court believing themſelves engag'd in Honour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing their ill uſage to the moſt Conſtant, at length either Sorrow or Miſery will bring them to their end: and then the reſt being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of this ſupport, and the hopes of Delivery, will endeavour to reconcile their Conſciences and their Underſtandings to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Religion, and of Politic Catholics will become Superſtitious. Zelots.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, if the King will be pleas'd to open his Eyes, and to free himſelf from the fear of a Civil War, while his Forces are employ'd againſt Foreigners, ſhall recall the Baniſh'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to the <hi>Reformed</hi> their Eſtates and Ancient Franchiſes, the greateſt part will return to their Country. Native Air, the Ancient Conſtitutions, and free Converſe with Kindred and Friends are ſuch powerful Attractions, which will much ſurmount the ſeeble remains of Fear; more eſpecially conſidering, that few of thoſe who fled for Sanctuary, but met with among Foreigners as great Advantages, as thoſe which they left at home.</p>
               <p>Either of which two things if they fall out, <hi>France</hi> will find her ſelf in nine or ten Years as peaceable, and formidable to her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as ſhe was under the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XII before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or toward the end of the Reign of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> IV. after the Edict of <hi>Nantes.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> are the beſt People in the World; if their Kings do but p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t confidence in them, they forget all the ill U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages they have receiv'd, and Sacrifice their particular Intereſt to the neceſſities of the State.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41191:31"/>During the Civil War, 1651. under the Minority of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. the Princes ſought the Alliance of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as being of their Religion; She aſſiſted them; but not with all that Vigour which good Policy requir'd. For the <hi>French</hi> Penſions had corrupted the greateſt part of her Counſellors. The Proteſtants had put <hi>Havre de Grace</hi> into the Hands of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who neglected to Succour them as they ought to have done. So that after the Battle of <hi>Dreux,</hi> the Princes were overjoy'd when propoſitions of Peace were made them When the Peace was concluded, they declar'd War againſt Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and Beſieg'd <hi>Havre de Grace.</hi> All the <hi>French</hi> flock'd thither, with an ardor more then ordinary, and the <hi>Hugonots</hi> in greater Numbers, then the Catholics. The Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> who Commanded the Place was aſtoniſh'd at this ſuddain Change, and endeavour'd to flatter the <hi>Reformed</hi> with new Hopes; to which they anſwer'd, that remiſs and faint-hearted Friends were more to be fear'd then reconcil'd Enemies.</p>
               <p>But if the Confederates vigorouſly preſs forward the Re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and will not admit of any Peace, but upon that Condition, they will gain the Hearts of the Proteſtants of that Kingdom, and may be aſſur'd of a ſtrong Party, that will look with an Evil Eye upon the Invaſion of <hi>Germany,</hi> conſidering it as a forerunner of the downfal of their Religion.</p>
               <p>The Re-eſtabliſhment of the Exiles, will be attended with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Benefit; without which the comfort of the reſt will be quite loſt, and Peace will prove a Misfortune; I mean, the <hi>ſurceaſing of the Perſecutions.</hi> I ſhall not trouble my ſelf to prove that forc'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions are contrary to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Goſpel, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to make Men Hypocrites then Chriſtians. 'Tis a Subject upon which others have proſperouſly exercis'd their Pens, and which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belongs to Theology then Policy: I ſhall only obſerve, that Intereſts of State obliges all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to force a Ceſſation of Perſecutions. 1. Becauſe they deprive them of their beſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. 2. Becauſe they inſpire others with the Spirit of Cruelty and Rebellion. 3. Becauſe they ſhake the very Foundations of Civil Society. 4. Becauſe they render the Government Feeble and Odious.</p>
               <p>Moſt certain it is, that Vertuous Perſons are the ſupport of a Kingdom, and that the Character of an honeſt Man is to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt his Conſcience. Let the Conſcience be erroneous or not, it always guides us to love Truth and Vertue, and to ſacrifice all things to that which the inward Light of our Underſtanding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41191:31"/>
to us as ſuch. So that when any one ſuffers loſs of Goods, Exile, Impriſonment or Death, becauſe he will not conform to a Worſhip which he believes to be forbidden by God, or profeſs an Opinion which he conceives to be falſe, it cannot be deny'd but that he Acts like an honeſt Man, tho perhaps he may be in the wrong.</p>
               <p>To this it may be objected, that if we admit this Rule, we ought to let go Robbery, Murder, Adultery and all other Crimes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſh'd, out of reſpect to them, who believe them to be no Sins. To which I anſwer, that there is no Toleration to be granted to thoſe that do not believe in God, nor the morality of the Goſpel; for that the Laws, which are the foundation of our Chriſtian <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publics,</hi> are ſo link't to the Precepts of Chriſt, that they cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without them. Add to this, that thoſe Precepts are ſo clear, that they who ſhould deny them, would be lookt upon as Prodigies, whom we might with good reaſon believe to be more malitious and wicked then ignorant, and that they were fitter to be lockt up for Mad-men, or to be puniſh'd as Diſturbers of the public Peace. But there is not the ſame judgment to be made of ſpeculative O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, which relate to the Eccleſiaſtical Government, or the forms of divine Service; the Number of thoſe that differ in thoſe things is almoſt infinite, and the wiſeſt Men many times wander ſo far from Truth in Reference to theſe Particulars, that they are pitty'd by their Opponents.</p>
               <p>Perſecution inſpires the Vulgar Sort, the Ignorant and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious with Cruelty, who are the Spectators, and frequently the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Miſchiefs which they cauſe others to ſuffer for the Truth. What can a Prince expect from a People accuſtom'd to Rob and Pillage their Neighbours, and to overwhelm them with Injuries, becauſe they had rather hear a Sermon then go to Maſs? Does not this infuſe a fear into them leaſt the Monks, Prieſts and Seditious Preachers ſhould turn the Fury of the Rabble upon their Soveraigns? The pretended Holy League, and the Tragical End of <hi>Hen.</hi> the III. one would think ſhould cauſe a trembling in the Joynts of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Princes.</p>
               <p>For a Prince to Perſecute his Subjects for Religion ſake is to ruin Trade: For that if the People make a public Profeſſion of it; and the Prince on the other ſide ſends his Dragoons to deprive them of their Liberties, to ſack their Houſes, waſte and confiſcate their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Impriſon or Baniſh them and their Families; In the midſt of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41191:32"/>
theſe Diſorders a great Number of Debts remaining unpaid will cauſe a great number of Bankrupts; beſides that vaſt numbers of poor People that were let to Work and got their Livings by thoſe that are Perſecuted, muſt be forc'd to ſtarve. All theſe Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences have befallen <hi>France,</hi> as it is well known. Nor does the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic exerciſe of the Reformed Religion being forbid, make e're a whit the better for thoſe that ſtay behind; for the Old Catholics will never truſt the News Ones, their Kindred or their Friends, of which they ſee ſome or other every day making their Eſcapes; nor will Foreigners either Traffic or ſend their Goods, to a Country where there is ſo little Security.</p>
               <p>Perſecution is an unexhauſtible ſource of Knavery, as affording Treacherous and Revengeful Perſons, an eaſie means to ruin their Adverſaries. An Attorney or Counſellor, that the Cauſe may go of his Clients ſide, has no more to do but to plead that their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Party is a frequenter of the private Aſſemblies of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that he rarely goes to Maſs, or that he ſpoke contemptibly of Tranſubſtantiation, or ſome other of the Tenets of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. There is no need of going into <hi>Italy,</hi> or <hi>Spain, Portugal,</hi> or the <hi>Indies,</hi> to find Examples for this. <hi>France</hi> it ſelf will furniſh us with a great Number within theſe few Years, and we might produce ſome more particularly, were it not that ſome Perſons are concern'd for whom We have too great kindneſs.</p>
               <p>After all this, there is no wonder that Perſecution renders the Government Odious; the fatal Conſequences of the Inquiſition are freſh in memory, and the great Oppoſition which was every where made againſt the ſetting of it up. It was expell'd out of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> reduc'd almoſt to nothing in the Venetian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and the <hi>Romans</hi> defac'd and pull'd down the Arms and Statues of <hi>Paul</hi> IV. out of their hatred to his memory for having impos'd that Yoak upon them. Almoſt all Perſecutors have been the Object of the Peoples Hatred, and their Ends have been ſuch for the moſt part as their Cruelties deſerv'd.</p>
               <p>The principal Strength of a King conſiſts in the Hearts of his People, ſo that when a Prince and his Miniſters are become Odious, the Government can never be ſaid to be ſtrong. A clear Example of which we ſee in <hi>James</hi> the II. But if that be not a proof ſufficient, becauſe <hi>England</hi> is altogether Proteſtant, let us call to mind the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> which the <hi>League</hi> reduc'd ſo low; the downfal of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> after the Union between the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41191:32"/>
Provinces</hi> and <hi>Guſtaphus Adolphus.</hi> Let us compare the Reigns of <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Philip</hi> II. of <hi>Charles</hi> the IX. and <hi>Hen.</hi> III. of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. and <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII.</p>
               <p>Therefore the ſhorteſt and ſureſt means to ſtifle the Spirit of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution is to procure the REUNION OF THE PROTESTANTS, who living in the ſame Communion would make a Body ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably Puiſſant, that the <hi>Roman Catholics,</hi> would not ſo much as think of diſturbing them. Thus we have ſet forth the Original of our Diviſions, the cauſes that have fomented them, and the hopes that we have of an approaching Union. We are not to ſhew that this reconciliation is not ſo difficult as People believe. All our Controverſies roul upon the ſame form of Eccleſiaſtical Government; upon the manner of Chriſt's being preſent in the Euchariſt, and upon the <hi>Idea</hi> of Predeſtination.</p>
               <p>As to the Eccleſiaſtical Government, I do not believe that any Proteſtant will deny me the following propoſitions that ſeem to be unqueſtionable, and of which there are ſome that are the foundation of our Reformation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a Church is a Body or Society of ſeveral Perſons that agree together upon certain Points of Doctrine, and upon a certain form of public Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That every Church in the Quality of a Body makes up a Part of the Civil Society, and every one of its Members is a Member alſo of the State: and conſequently that in that reſpect they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Soveraign Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That it is in the Power of the Magiſtrate to regulate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Government of growing Societies or of ſuch as are not yet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh'd by public Authority, and ſo grant them Laws and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That he cannot change the Government of thoſe which he finds already form'd, nor deprive them of their Rights and Priviledges; unleſs perhaps in ſome extraordinary Caſes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the Soveraign is Born Head of the Church he is a Member.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That there is no preciſe Form of Eccleſiaſtical Diſcourſe or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Government preſcrib'd in Hiſtory, or in the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Indeed we find there general Precepts to avoid Tyranny, Anarchy and Superſtition, to do all things with Decency and in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and to turn all things to Piety, and the Edification of the Faithful.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41191:33"/>7. That tho Epiſcopacy be the moſt Ancient of all Eccleſiaſtical Governments, becauſe the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> where the Goſpel was firſt divulg'd, was a Monarchy; Nevertheleſs the Form of Government is a thing indifferent of it's ſelf; and the beſt Diſcipline is that which beſt agrees with the Nature of the Goſpel, with the natural Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and Cuſtoms of the People, and the Conſtitution of the Government.</p>
               <p n="8">8. After the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> came to be diſmember'd, the ſeveral Soveraigns that ſhar'd it between them have as much right to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late within their own Dominions the Diſcipline of the Church, as the <hi>Chriſtian Emperors</hi> had. So that the Order of Presbytery can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Condemn'd in a Republic, where the Magiſtrate has made choice of it as the moſt conformable to the Government of the Country.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The laſt propoſition includes certain Conſequences which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire explanation. 1. That conſidering the preſent Conſtitution of <hi>Europe,</hi> a Univerſal Biſhop is a kind of a Monſter: and that it is alſo of dangerous Conſequence that a Biſhop, an Abbot, or other Prelate ſhould have a Juriſdiction over any part of the Clergy belonging to Neighbouring Princes. 2. That <hi>Oecumenic</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils are no more to be held, but by the Conſent of all the Chriſtian Princes; becauſe thoſe Councils were no more then General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Clergy of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> which is now no longer in being. 3. Suppoſing ſuch an unexpected Happineſs that all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> or the greateſt Part ſhould agree to call a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council, it would not be their buſineſs to handle Matters of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, nor of Diſcipline, of which it would be in vain to ſeek for a Uniformity; only to apply themſelves to examin the Differences among the Chriſtians about the Points of Doctrine, and to regulate, if it may be done, the Number of the Fundamental Articles, to determin what we ought to believe thereupon, and ſo to order it, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, notwithſtanding ſome few Controverſies of little Conſequence among them, may always ſtand their ground, look upon each other as Brethren, and Communicate with the ſame willingneſs upon all Occaſions together, as they obey the ſeveral Magiſtrates of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Countries through which they Travel.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Schiſm is a ſeparation occaſion'd by particular Perſons that forſake the Communion of a Church Authoriz'd by the Laws of a Kingdom to ſet up particular Congregations, and that only for ſome defect which they find in the Diſcipline of the Church, for ſome
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41191:33"/>
Ceremony, or for ſome Point of Doctrine not Fundamental. Thus the <hi>Labadiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> who differ from the reſt of the <hi>Reformed</hi> only about the time of the Adminſtration of the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> are <hi>Schiſmatics.</hi> The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> of <hi>Hungary</hi> are not ſo; but would be <hi>Hereticks,</hi> if the Doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> were true. The <hi>Catholics</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> who accuſe the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>England, Germany</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries</hi> of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> are Ridiculous: for that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of the <hi>North</hi> have as much right to regulate the Exterior Government of Religion, as thoſe of the <hi>South.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Schiſm is very dangerous; they who are the Promoters of it, will have much to anſwer for at the laſt day; and they who Harbour and Entertain it are no leſs Guilty. It is the Original of many Quarrels between private Perſons, and of Factions in the State: Add to this, that many times it happens that the Ringleaders of the weaker Party, for fear of being forſaken by their Followers, they fill their Heads with Opinions, which cauſe them to forſake in good earneſt the Communion of the lawful Church. We know what has happen'd to one Sect, which has made a great noiſe in the World, only becauſe a few Learned Men embrac'd their Party.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Ceremonies of themſelves are indifferent as to Religion. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs it is good to obſerve. 1. That the moſt Ancient are the beſt, and that they ought to be held in Veneration, tho they may be alter'd upon weighty and conſiderable Reaſons. 2. That all thoſe which have been reduc'd into the Church ſince <hi>Conſtantine</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſuſpected, becauſe of the Spirit of <hi>Paganiſm</hi> and Tyranny which began then to Reign. 3. That the Miſeries which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have ſuffer'd from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have inſpir'd them with an utter Abhorrency of all that has the leaſt Tincture of that Sect. So that it is both Prudence and Charity not to Scandalize other People, through an Affectation to imitate our Enemies in certain Words and Practices, which tho indifferent in their Nature, become baneful and miſchievous, becauſe offenſive to others. 4. That the Genius of our Age which is very much improv'd in underſtanding, and the Genius of the Chriſtian Religion, which relates all to the Soul and Conſcience, require few Ceremonies. 5. However that ſome are neceſſary to prevent the Contempt of Divine Worſhip and its Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the propoſitions that ſeem to me very profitable for the Peace of the Church, and which I judge to be ſo very clear, that I
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41191:34"/>
need not go about to prove them. The Reader alſo, I hope, will pardon my not drawing any Conſequences from them, in regard I write for a Re-union, and for that I do not deſire to give any Party an occaſion to Quarrel with me. Beſides there is no Perſon of a clear judgment, but can apply them himſelf; and for others they would be wrangling with me at every Turn.</p>
               <p>As to the manner how Jeſus Chriſt is preſent in the Euchariſt, there is no Controverſie perhaps ſo vain, nor more eaſie to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd: tho the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion imagin it to be the Foundation of our ſeparation. All the Proteſtants agree that this Sacrament is a Symbol of the Death of Jeſus Chriſt; a Commemoration of his Sacrifice, and a Pledge of the remiſſion of our Sins; that the Body and Blood of our Crucify'd Saviour, which are given us therein, are the Nouriſhment of our Souls; that we do not participate thereof but by Faith; and that the wicked do not receive Jeſus Chriſt, but only the Conſecrated Signs to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; That Jeſus Chriſt is not preſent but during the uſe of the Sacrament, that he is not to be there ador'd; that the Bread and Wine continue to be Bread and Wine after the Sacrament; and that we are not to pay any Religious Homage to thoſe Material E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements. So that all the difficulty is to know, how Jeſus Chriſt, who as Man is in Heaven can be at the the ſame time upon the Earth and preſent with the Faithful every time that they Communicate worthily. Upon which particular ſince the Scripture has not told us any thing, we ſhould do well to be ſilent.</p>
               <p>When I conſider and contemplate the unſearchable ways of God, I cannot conceive how two underſtanding Perſons, and endu'd with true Piety, can raiſe diſputes about Predeſtination and Grace. The ſame Perſon, who knows not either how Speech is Form'd, or by what Springs we our ſelves move, will undertake to teach others now God govern's the World, and what he has determin'd in reference to their equals. But to confound the Pride of Human Wit, it ſo falls out, that the more we reaſon upon theſe things the more we find that our underſtanding fails when we ſtrive to ſearch beyond the bounds of Divine Revelation. If they uphold Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination to be abſolute, they make God the Author of ſin, deſtroy Liberty and all Religion. If it be ſuppos'd conditionally, we cannot unfold the fore-knowledge of God, nor give any good reaſons for the varieties of his favours. Therefore let Men keep cloſe to that which is plain, and to what the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41191:34"/>
informs us in expreſs Terms. That God knows all things, and diſpoſes of all things as he pleaſes himſelf. That being the Maſter of Events, he is alſo of the heart of Man. Nevertheleſs that Man is free, that is to ſay, that he has Power to reſtrain his judgment in reſpect of <hi>True</hi> or <hi>Falſe,</hi> of <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil.</hi> That the habit of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and ſin decreaſes this Liberty, and that it increaſes by the good uſe which a Man makes of this underſtanding and divine Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. That God grants his Favour to all thoſe that deſire it; and ſo it is our duty to pray to him, to obey him, and to exhort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo to do, to impute all that is Evil to our ſelves, and all that is good to the Inſpirations of the Holy Spirit. This is that wherein all Chriſtians agree; and the whole being duly conſider'd the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute is reduc'd to one Impenetrable queſtion. It is a greed, that God ſhares out his benefits very variouſly, and that he diſtributes to ſome more, to ſome leſs. The difficulty is to know, whether God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords Grace ſufficient to ſave all and every Particular Man in caſe they make a good uſe of it. And who can affirm it Preciſely; at leaſt who can pretend to know the bottom of every Mans heart, and the degree of the Efficacy of that Aſſiſtance which he has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd?</p>
               <p>I will not undertake to deſcribe the Qualities to be requir'd in thoſe that ſhall be employ'd to accompliſh this Union. I make no queſtion but a fit choice will be made of Perſons of a Genius and Integrity more then ordinary. I ſhall only ſay, 'twill be more difficult to take care of making a good choice. They who have render'd themſelves odious to one of the Parties by their Writings embitter'd with Gall, are incapable to diſcharge this truſt, how learned ſoever they may be. There are ſome ſoaring Wits who ſway'd by I know not what Fantaſtical conceits, many times neglect things of great Importance, and apply their Studies wholly to Trifles. There are ſome ſo in love with Novelty that they would overturn all things elſe, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a ſuppoſition of their own Invention. Others under the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence of a Univerſal Union, would reduce Chriſtianity to Ideas ſo confus'd and general that natural Morality and Religion would with great difficulty be preſerv'd entire. Happy is he that can obſerve a juſt <hi>Medium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>France</hi> were humbl'd, Peace once ſettl'd, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> ſtrictly United, and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at reſt, we ſhould ſoon ſee the DOWNFAL of POPERY. But leaſt the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> ſhould be offended, they are to know that this is no deſir'd in reference to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41191:35"/>
what they look upon as the Fundamental part of their Religion: Let them pray to the Saints, let them adore the Sacrament, Images and Relics, if they think fitting; let them obſerve all their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; let them acknowledge the Pope for Head of the Church; this is nothing at all to us. We will be content, ſo that they will but ſolemnly renounce in expreſs Terms, and in a General Council, certain Opinions which the moderate among them openly deny, but yet are generally put in Practice 1. That it is in their power to Excommunicate and depoſe Heretic Kings, ſtir up their Subjects to rebel againſt them, diſpoſe of their Kingdoms to others, and rid their hands of Princes ſuſpected, by Aſſaſſination, or otherwiſe. 2. That Promiſes and Oaths made to Heretics are of no value; that they are not oblig'd to keep faith with them; and that they may be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and exterminated at all times as occaſion ſhall offer. At leaſt, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in a Body ſhall Anathematize all thoſe that are of theſe Opinions, or put them in Practice, ſince other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there is no Aſſurance for Princes or Private Perſons to conſide in any Treatys or Contracts which they ſhall make with thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh Communion.</hi> Or if they refuſe to Condemn this Hereſie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of <hi>Popery</hi> let them do it under the Name of <hi>Jeſuitiſm,</hi> which will very well agree with it.</p>
               <p>To the People there could be no Tydings more grateful then that of the ABATEMENT OF THEIR IMPOSITIONS; they are mounted to ſuch a Prodigious exceſs over all <hi>Europe</hi> unleſs it be in <hi>England;</hi> that there is hardly any other Country where a Man may live with convenience. The very Sciences are contemn'd, becauſe they are become mercenary. Arts periſh, by reaſon that the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency which oppreſſes the Artificers, hinders them from bringing any thing to perfection: and though they feel the Goads of Poverty, they are near a whit the more ſpurr'd on with the thoughts of Honour. The better ſort of Families are ruin'd, becauſe of the great expences of Houſe-keeping. The Country is diſpeopl'd of honeſt People, and fill'd with Vagabonds and Debauſhees, while the fear of Poverty deters an infinit Number of People from Marrying, and plunges others into wickedneſs and diſorder. There is nothing but cheating in Trade; and Men begin to be a weary of it by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, becauſe it becomes every day more dangerous, more difficult, and leſs gainful. The Subjects cheat their Soveraign; and to retali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate his Extortions, as they believe them to be, ſo generally accuſtom themſelves to deprive him of his rights, that they make no Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41191:35"/>
of it. All places, all Courts are full of Complaints murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, confiſcations, broken Merchants, and Law-ſuits. For the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of which <hi>Europe</hi> is beholding to the Court of <hi>France.</hi> To this Court are we beholding to thoſe tholes of Projectors, and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Prodigious Numbers of new Impoſts. But the worſt is, her continuance and dreadful raiſing of Armies, her Threats, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Breaches of Leagues and Truces oblige the Neighbouring Princes to keep on foot conſiderable Forces and conſtrain them at the ſame time to drain the Purſes of the Subjects. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idelburgh, Manheim,</hi> all the Palatinate, ſo many Countries, ſo many Cities which the <hi>French</hi> have laid waſt, ſackt, burnt, or deſtroy'd againſt all the Aſſurances of pleighted Faith; ſo many poor Creatures as the <hi>French</hi> Court has reduc'd to miſery by her Dragoons, Contributions, or rather juſtify'd Robberies are as ſo many Voices that cry for vengeance to Heaven, and which threaten all the Chriſtian Proten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates in the ſame manner, if they do not cloſely Unite to ſtop the Courſe of her fury.</p>
               <p>THE INCREASE OF TRADE, is one of the uſual Fruits of Peace and of the Abatement of Impoſts. But in regard the late Treaties of Peace were neither durable nor ſincere, but that both ſides continu'd ſtill in Arms, there has been no ſenſible Abatement of the Taxes, nor increaſe of Trade. Since the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen, France</hi> has laid a thouſand cruel Impoſts upon the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Trade, which their High and Mightineſſes made out in their <hi>Declaration</hi> of War againſt that Crown. But their Union with <hi>England</hi> preſents with an aſſured means and opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain double to what they have loſt. Thirty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſels are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to cruiſe upon the Coaſts of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Guyen,</hi> and to ſhut the <hi>French</hi> quite out of the entrance into <hi>Spain</hi> by Sea and ſtop up their Paſſage into the Streights of <hi>Gibraltar.</hi> Thirty <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Men of War will wreſt the Trade of the <hi>Baltic</hi> Sea and the <hi>Northern Ocean</hi> out of their hands, and keep the Coaſts of <hi>Picardy</hi> and <hi>Normandy</hi> in a perpetual Alarum. And then nothing will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main to the <hi>French</hi> but the <hi>Commerce</hi> of the <hi>Levant</hi> through the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> which will be more prejudicial then profitable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will drain the Coyn of the Kingdom, and overſtock it with wares which they will not be able to vend. The reaſon of it is becauſe the Cities of <hi>Italy</hi> all Trade the ſame way, and with more conveniences. Add to this that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> bring the ſame Merchandizes in great abundance out of the <hi>Levant</hi> and the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41191:36"/>
                  <hi>Indies,</hi> which only conſiſt in Drugs, Silks, Cotons, Wax, Hides, <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Leather, and Pot-aſhes. So that the <hi>French</hi> being debarr'd the Trade of <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> they will be ſtor'd with Goods but diſtitute of Money.</p>
               <p>Beſides the Trade of the <hi>Levant</hi> cannot extend but from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> to <hi>Lion,</hi> and be beneficial to ſome Cities only upon the <hi>Rhine:</hi> So that all the reſt of <hi>France</hi> and all the Coaſts of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> will never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs be depriv'd of their Trade, there being no vent for the Goods and Manufactures of the Country. We are aſſur'd, that about a Month ſince the ſtuff weavers were ready to have made an Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in <hi>Roven,</hi> upon Information that a Merchant of that City was about to ſet up a Royal Manufacture. They flew to his Houſe to the Number of four hundred, and conſtrain'd him to make a <hi>Declaration</hi> before the <hi>Intendant,</hi> wherein he proteſted that he never had any ſuch deſign, and ſolemnly promiſed never to enterprize the like again. If Poverty makes them ſo bold, what will they not dare, when thev come to feel the Nips of Pinching Hunger.</p>
               <p>'Tis a great Enterprize to bring down the Power of thoſe that make uſe of it meerly to do us miſcheif; but it is of far greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to provide for our own ſecurity. <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> joyn'd together will be Maſters of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and conſequently cannot ſtand in want of any thing. But though theſe two Nations may be ſtrongly Intereſted to preſerve their Union, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are ſtill more oblig'd to it then the <hi>Engliſh. Great Britain</hi> is an Inacceſſible <hi>Iſland,</hi> that ſtands in little fear of a Foreign Enemy. Whereas the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> may be attacqu'd by Land from the <hi>North, South</hi> and <hi>Eaſt.</hi> They are environ'd with Potent Neighbours, the <hi>Empire, France, Spain</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> And I dare be bold to ſay, that how powerful ſoever they may be in Wealth and Forces, in Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Territories, they are of too ſmall an Extent, to make head for a long time againſt any one of theſe their Neighbours without the Aſſiſtance of the other. This the <hi>States General</hi> rightly apprehended from the beginning of their Confederacy, while they had recourſe ſometimes to <hi>England,</hi> ſometimes to <hi>France,</hi> to ſupport themſelves againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria. France</hi> at this preſent time, is advanc'd to the ſame degree of Power in <hi>Europe</hi> which render'd <hi>Spain</hi> ſo formidable when firſt the <hi>Seven Provinces <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> together. And they have had experience in the laſt War, that <hi>France</hi> was no leſs eager after the Conqueſt of their Country then <hi>Philip</hi> the Second was to ſubdue them under his own, and the Tyranny of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41191:36"/>
Inquiſition. Of all their Neighbours there are not any, with whom they have greater tyes of Friendſhip then with <hi>Great Britain:</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that at this time the Intereſt of Trade is United to that of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And as if thoſe two tyes were not ſtrong enough, Heaven has bequeath'd one Prince to both, to Perpetuate their Union, and to the end thoſe two Nations may joyn together to break the Fetters which <hi>France</hi> was preparing both for them and all the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was juſt about to make an end, when the <hi>Sixth Letter concerning the Affairs of the Times</hi> came to my hands; where I read the Title and an Extract of three Libels againſt the Confederate Princes; but more eſpecially againſt His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> againſt whom <hi>France</hi> has the greateſt Antipathy. When Men are in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Paſſion, 'tis no eaſie thing to conceal it: Dread and Deſpair have ſeiz'd that Court: It is apparent by all they ſay, by all they do, and write. Now they flatter the <hi>Empire England, Holland,</hi> the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic</hi> Potentates, the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes, and in a Word all <hi>Europe,</hi> which they vaunted to be beholding to them for her Peace, and threatned not above ſix months ago with ſo much Haughtineſs. There is none to whom they give an ill Word but <hi>William</hi> the III. becauſe they ſee it would be a very Fruitleſs thing to flatter him. In all out ward appearance, they will gain as little by their Colloquing upon the reſt of the Princes. Since the Diet at <hi>Ratisbone</hi> has caus'd two of the three <hi>Libels</hi> to be Burnt by the hand of the common Hangman; and diſmiſs'd the Secretary to <hi>James</hi> II. However though the dread of <hi>France</hi> may ſeem to ſhew by her words, how far her Pride is abated, however we find the Traces of her rage and fury by the Devaſtations of her Troops, depopulating all with Fire and Sword. Is this the way to appeaſe the Princes of the <hi>Empire,</hi> by Sacking and Burning ſo many of the Cities; and waſting and deſtroying what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they cannot carry away?</p>
               <p>She expoſes the diſquiet of her thoughts by the reaſons which ſhe alledges, and by the manner of her venting them. They are only Invectives, Contradictions, and imaginary Suſpitions. 'Tis true, I never read thoſe three Pamphlets, but the <hi>Letters about the Affairs of the Times</hi> carry ſo fair a Character of ſound Judgment and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, that we may eaſily judge of the Reſemblance which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has to his own works. Never did Writer better ſupport his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; his Reflections neither offend through impertinency, not do the Spring from whence they flow ſeem to be in the leaſt exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41191:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
while the Author becomes every day more exact and more profound then other. After all not having ſeen any new reaſons in the Extract, I ſuppoſe I have refuted all Objections that our Enemies can alledge.</p>
               <p>However I am far from having drain'd my ſelf in reference to the Subjects which I have handled, that was not my intent; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing few of them which might not be enlarg'd to a conſiderable Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. Therefore I hope that the Omiſſions will not be charg'd upon me for faults, but that if I have ſaid thoſe things which are true and right, they will not be rejected for a ſlight Error. Beſides that I found my ſelf oblig'd to compoſe this Treatiſe out of hand, and in haſt, remote from my Study, my Friends, or any other Aſſiſtance, but a very great Zeal for the Public Good.</p>
               <p>I foreſaw ſeveral other Effects of a Union between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> which I did not think it proper to inſiſt upon, ſince they themſelves cannot but be ſufficiently ſenſible thereof. For Example. 1. That Arts and Sciences will Flouriſh, becauſe the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> love them, as being the Original of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> and therefore find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves at liberty, they will not fail to improve, ſo much the rather, in regard that King <hi>William</hi> the III. and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> the II. are ſo much the Favourers of Learned Men. 2. Becauſe the Laws of the Land will for the future be the Rule of Government; ſeeing that for their ſake the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> took up Arms and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd himſelf to ſo many dangers. 3. Becauſe that Juſtice and good Manners, will be more and more obſerv'd: in regard their Majeſties of <hi>Great Britain</hi> are themſelves both Juſt and Equitable, and the True Models of Vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
